<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pacis consultum: a directory to the publick peace: briefly describing, the antiquity, extent, practice and jurisdiction of several countrey-corporation-courts; especially, the court leet. An exact and perfect method to keep a court of survey for the setting forth and bounding of the mannors, lands, and tenements; with the articles to be therein given in charge: a work most useful: of which subject, never was any thing printed before. An abstract of the penal statutes, useful for all men to know. Also some difficult questions in law, proposed unto, and resolved / by Judge Jenkings.</title>
            <author>Jenkins, David, 1582-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1672_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115019</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115019)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 209:E1672[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pacis consultum: a directory to the publick peace: briefly describing, the antiquity, extent, practice and jurisdiction of several countrey-corporation-courts; especially, the court leet. An exact and perfect method to keep a court of survey for the setting forth and bounding of the mannors, lands, and tenements; with the articles to be therein given in charge: a work most useful: of which subject, never was any thing printed before. An abstract of the penal statutes, useful for all men to know. Also some difficult questions in law, proposed unto, and resolved / by Judge Jenkings.</title>
                  <author>Jenkins, David, 1582-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 135, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by J.C. for H. Fletcher, at the three gilt-cups, neer the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Judge Jenkings = David Jenkins.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, line 3 has "Publick"; line 8 has "Countrey"; the author's name is spelled "Jenkings".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 13.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Courts baron and courts leet --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>County courts --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115019:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pacis Conſultum:</hi> A DIRECTORY To the Publick Peace:
Briefly deſcribing, The Antiquity, Extent, Practice and Juriſdiction Of
ſeveral Countrey-Corporation-Courts; Eſpecially, The Court Leet. An Exact
and Perfect Method to keep a Court of Survey for the ſetting forth and
bounding of the Mannors, Lands, and Tenements; with the Articles to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
given in charge: a work moſt uſeful: of which Subject, never was any thing
printed before. An Abſtract of the Penal Statutes, uſeful for all men to
know. Alſo ſome difficult Queſtions in Law, propoſed unto, and
reſolved</p>
            <p>By Judge <hi>Jenkings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>H.
Fletcher,</hi> at the three gilt-cups, neer the weſt-end of <hi>Pauls</hi>
1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115019:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115019:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF any actions of men may be though praiſe worthy; certainly it
muſt be their endeavours for the publicke good; and above all, the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the common Peace, and propriety of <hi>meum</hi> and
<hi>tuum,</hi> one amongſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for which end and aim only, the Law was
ordained; <pb facs="tcp:115019:3"/>and to that very intent and purpoſe, was this enſuing
Treatiſe compoſed; not thereby to gain applauſe, but that others may by
it reap profit.</p>
            <p>For if the Country-Courts were duely kept as they ought to be,
both Court-Leet and Court-Baron in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Mannor, the common people need not
ſo complain for the want of due Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice, as they do;
nor be forced to ſeek ſo far, and trouble the Superior Courts with ſo
many petty Actions, wherein the damage can never countervail the charge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115019:3"/>
            <p>And for the Court of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey, as there is nothing more
neceſſary, ſo would it appear in the end, there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more
profitable: if the Lords and Tenants would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together in their ſeveral
Mannors, and cauſe Surveys and Terrars to be made of every one's Eſtate,
with the Title; and this keep as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt themſelves; thouſands
of tedious Suits, touching Titles of Land, to the undoing of many Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,
might be avoided, and the right Heir and Owner peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably enjoy his own, if
this courſe were taken but once in an age.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115019:4"/>
            <p>I the rather put down the Abſtract of Penal Statutes, becauſe
of the daily breach of them, to direct thoſe that will, how to puniſh the
Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders: and the voluminous bulk of the Statutes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves come not to
the view of every one. Gratefully therefore take this ſmall Branch, every one
that wiſhes well to the Peace of Engliſh <hi>Sion;</hi> for the Head and
Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers whereof, remains a daily Orator,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>27 <hi>April,</hi> 1657.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>Ph. Ag.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115019:4"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader, Theſe books following are printed for, and
ſold by <hi>Henry Fletcher,</hi> at the three Gilt-Cups in St. <hi>Pauls</hi>
Church-yard neer the Weſt-End.</head>
            <p>A Diſpenſatory, with the whole Body of Phyſick: wherein is
diſcovered the Natures, Properties, and Vertues of Vegetables, Minerals, and
Animals; by the learned <hi>Renodaeus,</hi> chief Phyſitian to the King of
<hi>France:</hi> Engliſhed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by <hi>Richard Tomlinſon</hi> of
<hi>London,</hi> Apothecary: in <hi>Fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Martyrology, containing a Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the Perſecution
that hath befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſince the firſt
Plantation of the Goſpel to the end of Queeh <hi>Maries</hi> Reign; with the
Lives of many Eminent Perſons: by <hi>Samuel Clearck.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>An Explication of the <hi>110 Pſalm:</hi> wherein the ſeveral
heads of Chriſtian Religion therein contained, are largely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained and
applied: by <hi>Edward Reynolds</hi> D. D: 4<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A plain and eaſie Caleulation of the <pb facs="tcp:115019:5"/>Name, Mark and
Number of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the
Beaſt, by <hi>Nathanie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in
<hi>Leiſterſhire:</hi> a learned
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paracti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his Chymical Tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Metals and Minerals, with the Experiments of <hi>Raymund
Lully,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the right Compoſition of both Elixirs: in
<hi>8<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Enchiridion</hi> of the Art of Phyſicks by <hi>John Sadler,
D.</hi> in Phyſick: <hi>8<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time well improved, or Meditations on Heavens glory, Earths
vanity, and Hells horror, with Prayers for moſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: and other
verſes uſed by the Bell man of <hi>London; 12<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>England's</hi> Balm, or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fals by way of Grievance and Remedy, to the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and
Parliament, for a Regulation of the Law by <hi>William Sheppard,</hi> Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant
at Law: in <hi>8<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Playes.</hi> The old Law; by <hi>Middleton</hi> in <hi>40.
Acteon</hi> and <hi>Diana,</hi> acted many times lately at the
<hi>Red-Bull,</hi> in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">0.</hi>
               </hi> both new.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115019:5"/>
            <head>The Antiquity, Extent, and Power OF Court-Leets; And the form
of keeping them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Antiquity may offer it ſelf in plea for Authority, then good
cauſe hath this Court to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge <hi>equality,</hi> if not
<hi>prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence</hi> above any in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England:</hi> for
it was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed long before the Conqueſt, and in thoſe days held
Plea of all matters in difference either for <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi>
the two greateſt Adverſaries in the world, or <hi>pro placitis
Coronae,</hi> which intends generally the keeping of common peace and welfare
in a Nation, which is the <hi>crown,</hi> and <hi>dignity</hi> thereof; and the
breach thereof is aptly <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115019:6"/>called <hi>Crimen leſae
Majeſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo duely and impartially in thoſe days were the Liberties
and Laws of this Court obſerved, that it is yet, and ever wil be recorded
amongſt our <hi>Legenda aurea;</hi> that in thoſe days a child might travel
ſafely in the Road with a bag of gold, without danger; and then the Ways were
more dangerous in regard of woods; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more full of Woods, but I think not
ſo well ſtored with Thieves as now; ſo that we have deſtroyed the one,
and yet in too much plenty reſerved the other.</p>
            <p>But to avoid digreſſions, and prolixity toe, we ſhall
proceed to the formality of proceeding in a Court-Leet as now it is: and by the
way, obſerve, that all manner of Crimes, from the higheſt Treaſon, to the
loweſt Treſpas, are here enquirable, though not puniſhable; of which in
order you ſhall have a perfect deſcription.</p>
            <p>A Court-Leet is at moſt kept but twice a year, in ſome places
but once, and in ſome lazie Lordſhips not at al, but left as a thing
obſolete and uſeleſs</p>
            <p>The manner thereof is, firſt about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days before the
Court is to be kept, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115019:6"/>for the Bayliff to give notice thereof
by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of a Precept to be by the Steward of the Court <hi>pro tempore
exiſtente</hi> to him directed; which uſually runs after this form.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Summons for a Court-Leet.</head>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ. A.
B. <hi>Gent. Steward of the</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, <hi>or</hi> Hundred, <hi>or</hi> Leet
<hi>aforeſaid To the Bayliff thereof, greeting: I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, that you
ſummon and warn all the tenants of the ſaid Mannor, as well reſidents as
not reſidents, and all cuſtomary tenants of the Mannor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, that
they be before me at H. aforeſaid on Thurſday the</hi> 26 <hi>day of</hi>
March <hi>next coming, to do their Suit unto the View of Frankpledge, and all
things thereunto belonging,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dated,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then the Steward ought to enter on the Court-Roll the Style of
the Court; which is uſually after this manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115019:7"/>
               <head>The Entry of a Court-Leet, together with a
Court-Baron.</head>
               <p>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ.
<hi>The view of Frank-pledge, with the Court-Baron of</hi> C. L.
<hi>
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Lord of the ſame, there held the</hi> 20 <hi>day
of</hi> March, <hi>&amp;c. By</hi> A. B. <hi>Steward there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then make three Proclamations when you call the Court; and then
a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Eſſoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and profers of Suit and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea: which if any be, enter them in the Court-Roll, and afterwards
proceed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and
ſwear the Jury for the Inqueſt. Swear firſt the Fore-man by himſelf,
and then the reſt by two or three at a time. The Oath is uſually the ſame
in ſubſtance, and not differing much in form from the Oath of the Fore-man
to a grand Inqueſt in Aſſizes and Seſſions, and might be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:
but leſt the young <hi>Tyroes</hi> might want it. I will in inſert the
method thereof, thus:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The form of the Oath to the Fore man of an Inqueſt at a
Court-Leet.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſhall diligently enquire, and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentment 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115019:7"/>make of all ſuch matters as ſhall be given you in charge:
the councill for the Lord Protector</hi> (Commonwealth, King, or other Title of
the ſupream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
as the Law commands) <hi>your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and your own, you ſhall well and truly
keep: you ſhall not conceal any thing for favour, fear, promiſe, or
affection, nor preſent any thing for lucre, hatred or malice; but in all
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings you ſhall
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth, according to
your evidence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So help you God, and by the contents of this Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Oath of the reſt may follow, in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All ſuch Oath as</hi> A. B. <hi>your Fore-man hath taken
on his part, you and every of you ſhall well and truly take, keep, and
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. So help you God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being done, and Proclamation made for every one to keep
ſilence and give attention, the Steward is to proceed to give the Charge,
which is to conſiſt of theſe particulars.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115019:8"/>
               <p>The Charge of a Court-Leet conſiſts of two parts: one is,
things there to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of, but not puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble there, and the other, ſuch offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces as are three pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentable,
and puniſhable by Fine, Amerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Know then, that, to avoid needleſs cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, we
ſhall briefly tell you, that a very proper compariſon may be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the diſpoſure of a Commonwealth and a natural Body, as between the
<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſmus</hi> and the <hi>Microcoſmus.</hi> The Commonwealth is a
Politick Body, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of a head and members, the one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient
to the other in his proper office, as the members of the natural body are;
which maintains a mutual harmony, and a flouriſhing condition in the whole.
But as the natural body is ſubject to infirmities ſo alſo is the Politick
and muſt be purged, the one by the Phyſitian, the other by the
Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>As in the natural body ſome diſeaſes are mortal,
ſtriking at the head thereof; ſome cannot be cured but by Blood-letting;
others ſo malignantly Gangreous, as the whole member muſt be cut off to
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſound part: ſo in the body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115019:8"/>there are ſome mortal diſeaſes, ſtriking at the head, as
Treaſons and Petty-trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as ſhall now be declared; ſome dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
wounding the members, as Murders, Manſlaughters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome
gangrenging, as Robberies, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lonios, Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>glaries, and the like, as follow.</p>
               <p>Orderly then; to eſcape confuſion, we ſhal declare what
offences are here at this Court-Leet enquirable and preſentable, and not here
puniſhable, but are by the Steward to be certified to the next Aſſize or
Seſſions of the County; and then what offences are here to be preſented,
puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and determined.</p>
               <p>The firſt of all preſentable here, are High-treaſons and
Petty-treaſons, which are diſeaſes ſtriking at the head, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,
if effected, to deſtroy the whole body.</p>
               <p>Preſentment therfore is here to be made of all High and Petty
Treaſons; which, together with ſome other crimes incurable but by taking
off the peccant member, are to be ſet down in writing intended; one part
whereof is to remain with the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard and the other with the Jury, and is to
be delivered to the Juſtices of Aſſize at the next general goal delivery
holden for the <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115019:9"/>County. <hi>Stamford; Pl. Coron. lib.</hi> 2.
<hi>cap.</hi> 24, and <hi>Lambert</hi> Juſtice of Peace, <hi>lib.</hi> 4.
<hi>cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>The Jury therefore is to enquire of all High-treaſons; that
is, if any do compaſs, imagine, intend, or go about to procure the death of
the Lord Protector, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the ſame by word, writing, or any open
act; or ſhall go about to make war againſt the ſaid Lord Protector and
this Commonwealth; or ſhall adhere to, or hold intelligence with any of the
Enemies of this Commonwealth: This is High-treaſon.</p>
               <p>If any perſon ſhall counterfeit, clip, file, waſh, or
otherwiſe counterfeit or falſifie any of the Coyn or Money of this
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, or the Coyn of any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is currant in this
Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; this is High-treaſon, and enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable here.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall counterfeit the Privy Seal, Signet, or Signe
Manual of the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> or any of
the mean Seals of the Common Pleas, Upper Bench, or Exchequer: Theſe are
High-treaſons, and to be enquired of here as Felonies.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115019:9"/>
               <p>Petty-treaſons are, if any man kill his Maſter or
Miſtreſs, or a woman her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this is to be enquired of here as
Felony.</p>
               <p>In the next place follows an unnatural wicked Crime to be
enquired of, and that is Murder. If any one ſhall out of malice prepenſed
or fore-thought, kill another; this is wilful Murther.</p>
               <p>Man-ſlaughter is alſo a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and
here to be enquired of: which is if two perſons fall out ſuddenly, without
any prepenſed malice, and fight, and the one kill the other; the Defendant in
this caſe ſhall have the book for his life, but loſeth his goods as in
the caſe of Murder: ſo ſhall alſo the Defendant loſe his goods, which
kills another <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> or in his own defence: and the ſame
Law is, if it be <hi>per infortunium</hi> by miſ-fortune: and this is here to
be enquired of, as Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
               <p>Rape is alſo here to be enquired of; that is, if any man lie
with, or carnally know any woman forcibly againſt her will, if ſhe exceed
the age of ten years, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe conſent afterwards; this is Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony by
the Statute, 22 <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. And if <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115019:10"/>there be any ayders
or aſſiſters therin, they are alſo adjudged Raviſhers, as well as he
that committed the act.</p>
               <p>Carnally to know any woman child under the age of ten years,
though ſhe do conſent, it is Felony.</p>
               <p>But in Rape there muſt be <hi>Rem in re,</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netration, as
well as <hi>emiſſiô ſeminis;</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is no Felony. A
Jury ought to be very Carefull herein, and not find a bill upon any Sluts
oath.</p>
               <p>Adultery is alſo to be enpuired of as Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony. If any man
carnally know anothers wife, and it be proved either by confeſſion or two
witneſſes, it is Felony: but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of one party is no
evidence againſt the other, nor a husband againſt his wife, nor a wife
againſt her husband.</p>
               <p>The <hi>horrendum peccatum non nominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> of man with man,
or with beaſt, is alſo Felony.</p>
               <p>Defacing of a mans Phyſiognomy, as cutting off his noſe,
putting out of eyes, or cutting out of a mans tongue, is Felony.</p>
               <p>Robbery is alſo here to be enquired of; that is, if any one
take any thing from the perſon of another violently, though it be but the
value of a penny; it is Felony.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115019:10"/>
               <p>If one be purſued by another, &amp; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in his
flight throw his purſe or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goods into a buſh or other place, and
the other comes and takes it, this is Felony as wel as if he took it from his
body, becauſ he parts with his goods for fear of his life.</p>
               <p>Burning of a houſe, or barn adjoyning to a houſe, is alſo
Felony, and here to be enquired of. Burglaries are alſo here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirable;
that is, if any perſon do break any houſe, Church, wall or gate, in the
night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time feloniouſly, though he carry nothing out of the houſe, yet this
is Felony, becauſe every mans houſe is his Caſtle wherein he ought to
repoſe himſelf for his ſafety, and out of which he is not bound to
flee.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhall diſcharge a Piſtol or any Gun in at a
window, this is Burglary.</p>
               <p>Alſo, robbing of Churches or Chappels, and taking any of the
ornaments or other goods out of the ſame, this is Felony.</p>
               <p>Taking of Doves out of a Dove-houſe in the night-time
feloniouſly, is Felony, and here to be enquired of.</p>
               <p>Alſo, taking of young Pigeons of Goſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawks in their n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſts; or taking of fiſh
fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniouſly out of ponds or trunks, is felony; but if out of a River, it is
but Trſpaſs.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115019:11"/>
               <p>Felonious taking of tame Dear, Swans marked, is alſo
Felony.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if any one receive a Felon, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Felony he
hath done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or if any reſcue any one that is taken for Felony, it is
Felony, and here to be enquited of.</p>
               <p>Acceſſaries are alſo here to be enquired of, which are of
two ſorts, both in Felony and Murder: that is, an Acceſſary before, and
an Acceſſary after the fact. An Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary before is; if any one
ſhall procure, command abet, or conſent to another to do a Felony, hough he
be not preſen: when he doth it, yet he is acceſſary before the fact.</p>
               <p>Acceſſary after the fact, is, when one conſenteth to it
afterwards, either by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Felon or his goods, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to be
ſtollen.</p>
               <p>Eſcapes are alſo here to be enquired of; which are of two
ſorts, voluntary and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent. Eſcape voluntary is, where one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
another for Felony, and afterwards permits him to go at large whether he will:
this is Felony.</p>
               <p>A negligent Eſcape is, when one is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted for Felony, and
afterwards eſcapas, through the negligence, though againſt the will of his
Goaler or Keeper: and if he be <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115019:11"/>not freſhly purſued and
taken, before they loſe the ſight of him, the Goaler ſhall therefore
ſuffer a Fine.</p>
               <p>Petty Larceny is alſo here to be enquired of; which is the
felonious taking of any thing under the value of 20 d as Hens, Geeſe Piggs;
or pilfering things of ſmall value out of wincows: theſe things are here to
be enquired of For theſe offences, <hi>The houſe of Correction were mere
proper for the offendor, then the Goal and puniſhment uſed: &amp; ſo
likewiſe more ſatisfactorily might all Felonies be expiated by the Felons
labour till reſtoration be made, then by death; For tex talion is, it the
moſt juſt law in the world; bloud requires blood and nothing elſe; it is
more precious then to be ſpilt as to often it is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But while it is as it is, you are to enquire what Goods or
Chattels, Lands and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments any Felon hath at the time of the Felony
committed: for the perſons ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending forfeit their goods to the Lord of
the Leer, and their lands are to eſcheat to the Lord of whom it is
holden.</p>
               <p>And thus mach concerning ſuch matters and offences as are to
be enquired of and preſented a a Court-Leet, and to be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the
Juſtices of Aſſize. In the next <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115019:12"/>place follows ſuch
things as are here to be preſented and puniſhed.</p>
               <p>This being a Court of Record, here may be brought Informations
upon all penal Statutes, or an action of Debt, at the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the
Plaintiff or Informer.</p>
               <p>Offences of this nature in this Nation, do at this time too much
abound; parly by the Ignorance of ſuch as would proſecure them, but know
not the Law, nor the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; and chiefly by the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of thoſe
that ſhould take cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of them and puniſh them but they are more apt
to incline to take the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents part then the Proſecutors. Know
therefore, that amongſt theſe Caterpilers of the Commonwealth, the
Gameſter is the principal Verb: by which wicked pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, how many Families
and perſons are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruined! And yet none ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured and
defended theſe.</p>
               <p>But to prevent this deſtructive evill, the Law hath provided,
that if any man ſhall keep, either in his houſe, yard, or backſide any
playing, or ſufferany to play at Tables, Cards or Dice, Coits, Claſh,
Loggets or Nine-pins, Shove-groat, otherwiſe called Slide-thriſt, or
ſhall keep any Bowling-green <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115019:12"/>or alley, and ſhall
ſuffer any perſon to play therat, or at any other unlawfull game, either
now invented, or to be invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; every ſuch perſon and perſons ſhal
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit 40 <hi>s</hi> a day for every day wherein he kept ſuch gameing as
aforeſaid: And all perſons that ſhall play at any ſuch games, forfeit
every one the ſum of 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day that they
ſhall play at any ſuch games as aforeſaid: one moyty of all ſuch
Forfeitures ſhall go to the uſe of the Lord Protector, the other moyety to
any perſon that will ſue for the ſame <hi>(non conſtat, what he is
worth per annum, as ſome pretend)</hi> in any Court or Cours of Record,
either by action of Debt, Bill of Indictment, Plaint, Suit, or Information;
wherein no wager of Law, Eſſoyn or other protection is to be allowed the
Defendant. Therefore in this Court, an Information, action of debt, or Plant,
lies againſt gaming-houſes, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers therat, if any ſuch there be
within the Juriſdiction of the Leet <hi>(as there are few places free from
them)</hi> And the Jury is alſo to inquire of theſe offences, &amp;
preſent them.</p>
               <p>In the next place, (and indeed, be ought to be a the upper end
of the board) for he's the ringleader of all wickednes) comes 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115019:13"/>Mr. <hi>Ale-houſe keeper,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Victualer,</hi>
as he calls himſelf: This is one that is ſeldom guilty of one fault alone;
yet he's ſo eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the vapours of his Ale, that he'll bid defiance to
the law, and them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it: and many times the Conſtable, or him
that is ſworn to preſent his Abuſes, dares not, becauſe out of the
fluſhes of his eaſie gains, he lends him money.</p>
               <p>But the Jury, at every Leet and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is ſworn to
enquire and preſent, if any one ſell Beer or Ale without licenſe. It will
not ſerve their turns, to pretend they are free Cooks, or free Inholders: for
the ſtatute excuſes none. The puniſhment for an unlicenſed
Alehouſe-keeper is at the diſcretion of the Judge or Juſtice, either by
the thee Statute of 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. wherein the penalty is 20 <hi>s.</hi> to
the uſe of the poor (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting a third part to the Informer, if it be by
information) of the pariſh where the offence is committed; or in default of
pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, the Ale Merchant is to be publickly whipt. Another penalty by
the Statute of 3 <hi>Car.</hi> is three days Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without Bayl: and
for Mainprize, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards until he ſhall put in ſufficient ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
not to Victual any more without Licenſe.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115019:13"/>
               <p>Alſo, if any Alehouſe-keeper, litenſed or unlicenſed
ſhall ſell Beer or Ale in unſealed Meaſures, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cans, ſtone-Juggs, black Pots or the like, or
in any other unſealed Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or ſhall ſell leſs then a full
Ale-quart of the beſt Ale or Beer for a peny, or take above a peny for a full
ſealed quarr; he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits for every ſuch offence 20 <hi>s.</hi> one third
part thereof to the proſecutor, and two parts to the poor of the
Pariſh.</p>
               <p>Honeſt then might well employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to puniſh
theſe Offenders: and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it impartially, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
may do much good to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, preventing theſe fellows from growing
from bad to worſe, by putting their ill-gotten, gains to Uſury; maugre
their calling of them <hi>Promoting knaves.</hi> And I doubt not but I ſhall
have ſuch pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as the Chaplains of their Calling nſe, for my pains.</p>
               <p>If any Al-houſe keeper ſhall ſuffer any perſons to ſit
tipling in his houſe above the ſpace of an hour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he forfeits Ten
ſhillings, and the Tiplers Ten groats a piece:</p>
               <p>If any Alehouſe-keeper ſuffer any one to be drunk in his
houſe, the Drunkard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits 5 <hi>s.</hi> the Alehouſe-keeper 10
<hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115019:14"/>
               <p>Every Alehouſe-keeper is to keep at leaſt one lodging-bed in
his houſe, for the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of Arangers: that is the intent of
Alehouſes.</p>
               <p>Neither is the Alehouſe-keeper to take any goods to pawn, of
ſtrangers or way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men; nor to entertain any ſuſpicious perſons,
but to give notice thereof to the Conſtable or next Juſtice of peace.</p>
               <p>Fore-ſtallers, Regrators, and Ingroſſors, are here alſo
to be preſented or informed againſt.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhall buy corn upon the ground, or other dead
victuals, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſell it again out of any Fayr or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, he
forfeits the value of the goods ſo bought, and two months impriſonment of
his body, without Bayl or Mainprize.</p>
               <p>There is alſo an Act of Parhament late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made concerning Corn
and Meal, That if any perſon ſhall ſell or put to ſale any Meal or
Flour, in his houſe or ſhop, or otherwiſe then in the open &amp; publike
Market; be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits the treble value of the Meal or Flour ſo ſold: one
half of which forfeitures go to the poor of the Pariſh where the offence is
committed; the other half to any one that will ſue for the ſame in any
Court of <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115019:14"/>Record by Information, Indictment, or Action of
Debt. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And moreover; the Meal-man is to ſuffer impriſonment
of his body the ſpace of one month, without Bayl or Mainprize.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhall ſell wine without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, he forfeits
five pounds a day for every ſuch offence; one half to the Protector, the
other half to the Proſetutor.</p>
               <p>If any one ſhall uſe any Art, Myſtery, or Manual
Occupation, having not been brought up Apprentice thereunto by the ſpace of
ſeven years, he forfeits fourty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a month for every month he
ſhall ſo uſe it; one half of the Forfeiture to the Protector, the other
to the Proſecutor.</p>
               <p>If any perſon, of the age of ſixteen years or more, ſhall
wilfully abſent himſelf from his Pariſh-Church, and ſhall not repair
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto or ſom other lawful Pariſh-Church or Chappel, during the ſpace
of a month, he forfeits for every month he ſhall ſo refuſe going to
Church, and not having a lawful excuſe to the contrary, the ſum of 20
<hi>l.</hi> the Forfeiture to be divided in three equal parts; one third part
thereof to go to the Lord Protector, the other third part to the Poor of the
Pariſh where the offence is <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115019:15"/>committed, and the other
third part to the Informer; to be recovered in any Court of Record, by any
perſon that will ſue for the ſame, by Action of debt, Indictment, Bill,
Plaint, or Information. <hi>I ſee noreaſon why Anabaptiſts; and thoſe
called Quakers and Rantors to, ſhould be exempted from the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of this
Statute, any more then Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi> But further to proceed to our
Charge.</p>
               <p>The Jury is to enquire alſo, if all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables,
Headburroughs, Deoimers or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingmen, and all other Suitors that owe any Suit
unto this Court, be preſent here or not, to do their Suit and Service; and to
preſent the names of all that are abſent, or make default.</p>
               <p>They are alſo to enquire if any Cuſtoms or Services due unto
this Court be conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or holden back, how or by whom the ſame are ſo
detained; and in what Bayliffs time the ſame was; and preſent the
ſame.</p>
               <p>Enquiry is alſo to be made, if any <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſtures</hi> be
made upon the land, wood, or water, with blocks, ſtaves, ditches, hedges, or
by or with any other thing, manner or way done to the common an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance of the
people; and preſent it.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115019:15"/>
               <p>Alſo, if any Walls, Houſes, Pale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or Hedges, be made or erected
within the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of this Court, to the annoyance of the people: this
is to be here preſented.</p>
               <p>If any High ways, Waters, Ditches or Paths be turned aſide out
of their andient courſes; this is to be enquired of, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
               <p>The Jury is alſo to enquire if any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments be made on
the High ways, or upon any of the Lords ſoil or common, or one neighbour upon
another; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the ſame.</p>
               <p>If any Layſtalls be made or any carrion be caſt in
High-wayes; this is enquirable.</p>
               <p>Common diſturbers of the peace, or ſuch as make Frays in
diſturbance of the people or breach of the peace; this is to be
preſented.</p>
               <p>If there be any common Barretors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the juriſdiction of
this Leet, common Scolds, or makers of debate, to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance and
diſturbance of their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; this is enquirable.</p>
               <p>Enquiry is alſo to be made of all Pound, breakers, ſuch as
break the common Pound, to take any Diſtreſs out of the ſame; their names
are to be preſented.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115019:16"/>
               <p>Alſo, the Jury is to enquire, if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall make
any Outcries againſt the Law, (where no cauſe is) to the diſturbance of
the people; and preſent their names.</p>
               <p>Alſo if any Reſcous be made within the juriſdiction of
this Court, upon the Sheriff, or any of his Bayliffs, or any other Officers, in
the execution of their Office; this is to be enquired of and preſented.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo if any Eves-droppers, that is. ſuch as ſtand
under walls, windows, at dors or other places, to hear the diſcourſe of
others, and to carry tales thereof to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, thereby to make debate or
ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their neighbours; preſent their names<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>All
ſuch offenders are to put in good ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ourity for their good behaviour; the offence highly deſerving
it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Breakers of hedges, and ſuch as walk by night and ſleep by
day, are here to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of.</p>
               <p>All ſuch as keep houſes of Bawdry, or ill orders in their
houſes, to the breach o the peace, or diſturbance of their neighbours,
their names are to be preſented.</p>
               <p>All common hannters of Taverns or Ale houſes, having not
viſible eſtates ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to live upon, they are here to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115019:16"/>of, and preſented, that they may give an account by what
means they live. And under this Article, being well and duly examined to the
purpoſe, you will finde many Thieves and Gameſters; from which number, my
hoſt himſelf is ſeldom to be excluded.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if any go in any meſſuage for Thieves, knowing them
to be Thieves, they are to be enquired of.</p>
               <p>If any perſon have watered any Hemp or Flax in any river,
running water, ſtream or brook, or common Pond. where cattel uſe to drink,
they are to be enquired of: they forfeit for every ſuch offence 20
<hi>s.</hi> the one moyty to the party grieved, or any man that will ſue for
the ſame in the Court-Leet, by Action of debt, Bill, Plaint, or
Information.</p>
               <p>But note, that if ſuch an offence be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Jury
in a Court-Leet, the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty cannot be levied, but the offender is there to be
amerced, and the Amerciament eſtreated, and ſo levied: but it may be
puniſhed in the Leet, upon the Action or Information of any perſon
againſt the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender.</p>
               <p>If any perſons have or uſe any falſe, counterfeit, or
unſealed Weights, Scales or <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115019:17"/>Meaſures; or if any uſe
double or two ſorts of Weights or Meaſures, that is, one to ſell by, and
another greater Weight to buy by, which is a deceit to the people; this is to
be enquired of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</p>
               <p>The Aſſize of Bread is alſo to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of; and it
wants diligent enquiry whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bakers do make their bread of a due ſize
according to the Statute, and the rate and price of corn; and preſent the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulters.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if Butchers, Fiſhmongers, or any other Victuallers,
ſell any corrupt, or offer to put to ſale any corrupt or unwholeſome
fleſh or fiſh, it is to be enquired of. Alſo, that all perſons that
ſell Victuals, ſell the ſame at reaſonable prices, according to the
price of the Market adjoyning: and they that ſell otherwiſe, and are
thereof convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall pay double what they receive, to the party that is
damnified: this is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be enquired of.</p>
               <p>Euquity is alſo to be made of Hoſtiers, that they ſell not
Hay or Oats but at rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable prices; and that they do not take for the
buſhel of Oats but an half-penyover the common price in the Market; and that
they take nothing for the Litter.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115019:17"/>
               <p>An Inne-keeper may bake his bread for horſes, in his houſe,
in any thorowfare-Town, which is no City where any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bakers dwell.
Provided that he make the ſame according to the prices of grain: otherwiſe
it is preſentable and puniſhable in Leet.</p>
               <p>If any Millers take exceſſive Toll, they are to be enquired
of. A Miller ought to take but the twentieth, or the four and twentieth grain,
according to the cuſtom, or the ſtrength of the water.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if any Miller change the corn or grain he hath ground,
it is here enquirable and puniſhable.</p>
               <p>If any Artificers uſe any deceit in their work to the
deceiving of the people, it is here to be enquired of, and their names p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſented.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if any Conſtable, Ale-taſter, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, or any
other Officers within his juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of this Court, have not well and
truly done their Officers, or neglected the ſame, it is to be enquired of and
preſented.</p>
               <p>Whether the Conſtables and Tything<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have done their
endeavors to ſee the peace kept, and duly to keep watch and ward as the Law
requires; it is to be be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of here and preſented.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115019:18"/>
               <p>The Jury is alſo to enquire of Treaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trove; that is if
any Money, or Plate, or other treaſure be found, that was hid in the ground,
and no man knows the owner, that is, who hid the ſame; this is the King's,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Lord have it by a ſpecial Grant or Preſcription.</p>
               <p>Enquiry is alſo to be made of Eſtrays; that is, if any
Horſe, Piggs, Hoggs or other
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attel, or Swans have come
into this Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and have been there a year and a day, and not claimed;
then the ſame is the Lord's by Preſcription: but the ſame ought firſt
to be impounded in a lawful Pound, and proclaimed in three Markets next
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning: and if one claim them, then they ſhall be ſeized, and ought to
be put into ſome ſeveral land, which is open and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and not into any
covert, or wood, where the owner cannot finde them: for if they be in covert
the property is not chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though they be there a year and a day</p>
               <p>Waifs are alſo to be enquired after; that is to ſay, Whether
any Thief upon Hue and Cry, purſuit or otherwiſe, doth waif his goods, that
is, throw away or forſake his goods or any part thereof in his flight, ſuch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115019:18"/>goods are called Waifs, and the Lord of the Leet is
ſeized thereof: therefore it ought to be enquired of, and preſented here at
this Court. Alſo, if any Officer ſeize upon any Thieves goods, though there
be no purſuit; in this caſe, the Lord of the Leet ſhall have theſe
goods.</p>
               <p>If any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for
Felony or Murder; that is, if any be indicted for Felony or Murder; though he
be acquitted, yet if it be found that he fled for the fact, he forfeits his
goods and chattels to the King, or to the Lord by Charter: and this is
enquirable.</p>
               <p>If any horſe or mare that is ſcabbed, mangie, or hath any
infectious diſeaſe, be put into any Common or waft grounds; the owner
thereof ſhall forfeit to the Lord of the Leet 10 <hi>s.</hi> this therefore
is to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of.</p>
               <p>If any perſon be outlawed in Debt, Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, or other
perſonal Action, his goods are forfeited, and the King ſhall have them,
unleſs they be granted unto the Lord by Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this is alſo here enquirable.</p>
               <p>The Jury are alſo to enquire whether the common Fyne is duly
gathered by the Bayliff or Headborough, and paid accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cuſtom of
the Court, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115019:19"/>
               <p>They are alſo to enquire whether there be within the Leet a
Pilloty, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umbrel, and
Stocks, to puniſh offenders according to Law. In every town where there is a
Leet, there ought to be Stocks; and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault thereof, the Town ſhall
forfeit, 5 <hi>l.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any Baker, Butcher, Brewer, Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, or the like,
dot ake exceſſive gain for their Victuals, or do promiſe, covenant or
conſpire together, not to ſell Victuals but at a certain price, this is to
be here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of and preſented.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, enquiry is to be made if any Artificers, Workmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Labourers have promiſed,
covenanted, or conſpired together that they will not make or do their works
but at a certain price, and not to finiſh what another hath begun, or that
will do but certain work in a day; they are to be preſented, and puniſhed
according to the Statnte of 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8, <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Alſo, enquiry is to be made if any Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner have put to ſale
any Hide of Ox, Bul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Cow,
that is gaſhed or out: he ſhall forfeit for every Hide ſo ſold, 12.
<hi>d.</hi> Alſo, no Curryer ought to curry any Leather in a Shoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>makers houſe, nor to curry any
Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is evil tanned.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115019:19"/>
               <p>Enquiry is to be made in all Leets in Country-towns and
Villages, if there be any Crow-nets to deſtroy Crows and Rooks, if they do
not deſtroy the Crows neſts then they begin to breed: in default hereof,
the Town is to be amerced.</p>
               <p>You are alſo to enquire in the Leet, if any perſon hath by
any means taken or killed the young Spawn or Fry of any Fiſh, in any
ſtream, river, brook, floud-gate, or in the Tayl of any Mill; or whether any
perſon hath taken in any of the ſaid places any Salmons or Trouts out of
ſeaſon, or any Pikes not being in length ten Inches, or any Barbel not
being in length twelve inches, or any Salmons not ſixteen inches, or Trouts
not eight inches: all ſuch offenders are here to be enquired of, preſented
and puniſhed.</p>
               <p>The Jury ſhall alſo enquire, if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall either
by day or by night break down the head or dam of any Pond, Pool or Moat,
wherein the Lord hath fiſh, with an intent to ſteal or deſtroy the ſaid
Fiſh; he ſhall pay to the Lord treble damages, and be impriſoned three
months, and be bound to the good behaviour for ſeven years.</p>
               <p>Hunters and ſtealers of Deer are here to be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquired of and
preſented.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115019:20"/>
               <p>No ſtone horſe, being of the age of two years, ſhall be
put into any common, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or Chaſe to paſture, except he be fourteen
handfulls high, in pain to forfeit the ſaid horſe. Alſo, the ſaid
Commons ought to be driven at <hi>Micha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lmas,</hi> or within fifteen days after, upon pain of 40
<hi>s.</hi> and if upon the ſam driving there be found any Mare Foal, or
Gelding, not likely to be able to bear foals, or do other profitable ſervice,
the ſame ſhall be ſlain and buried. 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap</hi>
13.</p>
               <p>You ſhall alſo enquire whether Hue and Cry, and freſh Suit
be duly made and purſued, after Robbers and Felons, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute
of <hi>Weſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13
<hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. For if any man be robbed in the day-time, and
the Thief eſcape, and is not taken within fourty days after the Robbery, for
lack of Hue and Cry, the Burrough or Hundred ſhall anſwer to the party for
his damages. Alſo, if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be killed in the day-time in a Town,
&amp; the Murderer or Manſlayer eſcape, the Townſhip ſhall be fined for
his eſcape 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>If any perſons, to the number of twelve or above, ſhall make
any unlawfull aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115019:20"/>to break any Banks,
Incloſures, Parks, Barns, Houſes, and ſuch like, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations be
made by the Sheriff or Juſtice of Peace that they depart, and yet if they
remain together an hour after ſuch Proclamation is made, every ſuch attempt
is Felony.</p>
               <p>Alſo, every Copy-holder, being a Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Husbandman or
Labourer, of the age of 18 years, and under 60, not ſick, not having a
reaſonable excuſe, and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the Juſtice, Sheriff
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſuch riotous perſons as aforeſaid, and
refuſe, ſhall forefeit his eſtate during life, and his Lord may enter.
Alſo, the Farmer being a Yeoman, and refuſing, forfeits to his Landlord,
and he may enter.</p>
               <p>Alſo, it is Felony, if any perſon, without compulſion,
bring, ſend or diliver any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Ammunition or Victuals to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
aſſembled in ſuch manner. Alſo, the Juſtice of Peace, or other
Officer, may raiſe a power to ſuppreſs them. And if any Officer kill any
ſuch Riotous or rebellious perſons, he ſhall go free.</p>
               <p>And if any perſon know of any ſuch pretended rebellion,
&amp; do not openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the ſame within twenty, hours next 
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115019:21"/>after ſuch knowledge, he ſhall be impriſoned three
months without Bayl or Mainprize: and alſo, he that hindereth Proclamation
that it cannot be made, commits Felony.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall trace in the Snow, kill or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy any Hare or
Leveret with dogs or otherwiſe, he ſhall forfeit 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8
<hi>d.</hi> 13 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>If any Jury ſworn and charged to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire concerning theſe
offences, do wilfully conceal the ſame, then the Steward hath authority to
impannel and charge another Jury to enquire of ſuch concealment. And if
ſuch concealment be found and preſented by the ſaid Jury, then every one
of the firſt Jury ſhal forfeit for every concealment of every offence 20
<hi>s.</hi> one moyety thereof to the Lord of the Leet, the other moyety to any
one that will ſue for the ſame by Action of debt, Bill, Plaint, Suit, or
Information: wherein no wager of Law, Eſſoyn, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection is to be
allowed. Provided the Suit be commenced within ſix months; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the
offender to be diſcharged thereof. 33 <hi>H.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p>Stewards in Leets have power to enquire concerning the erecting
of Cottages, and maintaining of Inmates, and to puniſh by <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115019:21"/>Diſtreſs al offences committed againſt the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te touching Inmates and
Cottages. 31 <hi>Eliz cap.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Stewards in Leets have alſo power to enquire, hear and
determine all offences touching the making of Malt. 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6.16.
<hi>Ed.</hi> 2.35. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Stewards in Count-Leets ſhall enquire of, hear and determine
al offences commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within their Liberties againſt the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the
preſervation of Pheſants and Partridges. 23: <hi>Eliz.</hi> 6.23.
<hi>Eliz</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, with a <hi>ſalvo jure</hi> to all
Corporations and Bodies Politick, of all their rights and priviledges, to
enquire and puniſh any of the ſaid offences 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 17.35
<hi>Eliz.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Articles to be given in charge to Conſtables and
Headboroughs, at Leets and Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions both of Cities, Towns, and Country
Corporations; moſt neceſſary for the preſervation of Peace, to which
our preſent ſcope intends only: and this Direction well followed, will
perfectly conduce thereunto, if ſuch a preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for the health of men
can be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto under Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115019:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore I ſay, Theſe enſuing Article ought
ſpecially to be enquired of, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and preſented by all Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
Headboroughs, Tythingmen, Decimers and all ſworn officers, who are enjoyned
by Oath to preſerve the Peace in their own perſons, and in all others as
much as in them lies; then to diſcharge their own duties, let them,
diligently obſerve and proſecute what follows, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inprimis,</hi> They are to enquire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn al ſuch
perſons as ſhal continue tipling or drinking in any Innes or Alehouſes,
at any time above the ſpace of an hour, and more eſpecially upon the
Sabbath-days: and ſuch perſons as they ſhall find drunk, and alſo
ſuch In keepers and Alehouſe-keepers as ſhall entertain them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are alſo to return the Names, Sirnames,
Additions of Names and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of all Popiſh Recuſants; (as wel
houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, as Lodgers) dwelling or reſiding in any of their Pariſhes,
Precincts, or Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Names of ſuch perſons as ſhall profanely
ſwear or curſe, with the number <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115019:22"/>of their Oaths or
Curſings immediately after the committing of ſuch offence.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Item,</hi> Such as uſe victualling or ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
Beer or Ale without Licenſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Such perſons as ſuffer any unlawful Games in their
houſes, backſides, or Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: and alſo the Names of any that ſhall
play at any of the ſaid Games. This is a gangrene and ſpreading leproſie
in this Commonwealth, a Vice abhorent to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; yet (the mores the
pitty) moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by them that ſhould ſeek to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it, I
mean, in plain Engliſh, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Law: inſomuch, that an
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt cauſe ſhal never have any countenance or defence like one of
theſe: and no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſo much vilified; nay, a Felon ſhall have
more favor then a lawful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, I mean an Informer againſt theſe
Caterpillers: <hi>Sed tu domine uſque quo?</hi> But <hi>nolens, volens,</hi>
(yet I hope to ſee the contrary), Mr. <hi>Alehouſe-keeper</hi> will be the
beſt man; yet I hope to ſee the tide run the contrary way, if men could but
once learn wit enough to know, That <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity begins at home;</hi> The
Alehouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper knows it very well: he'll be ſure to look how the reckoning
goes: and wiſe <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115019:23"/>men will keep reckoning at home, and not
let him keep it for them; knowing that two pence a day is above fifty
ſhillings <hi>per annum,</hi> and out of two pence the Tap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merchant gets a
penny. Then judge what he gets by all the Flyes he catches in his Web.
Certainly, did people once conſider this, the Ale wife would have few
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions better then her ſelf, yet now ſhe thinks the beſt ſcarce
good enough for her, though the Cauſers of it have little thanks for their
pains: when ſhe hath gotten their money, it's ſeldom but they have a
ſcoff or jeer into the bargain, becauſe they ſhould not complain of an
unkind Hoſteſs: And the worſt miſchief of all, is, That men very often
inſnare themſelves to their, utter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing by the Alehouſe-keepers and
his <hi>Compurgators Eveſdropping</hi> of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. And certainly
none but fools will go to <hi>game</hi> for what is already their own, nor no
Chriſtian endeavour to come by, or enjoy by playing for what is anothers. And
becauſe the Fort and Fountain of Gameſters is the Alehouſe, I made this
Digreſſion ſoberly to adviſe three ſorts of men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The one is in general all honeſt people to <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115019:23"/>wiſh them (if they be not worſe then In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels) to avoid the
Alehouſe; for under that notion I conclude the gaming houſe too, knowing
them to be inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions. And therefore I ſay again, It were well
if it were ordained, That every Alehouskeeper ſhould have at his door the
ſign of the Begger; for from that ſpring, the Alehouſekeeper original
comes when he firſt enters into his order; and before he leaves, he makes all
Beggers that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent his company: therefore ſuch a ſign might give
warning to others to let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and keep his beggerly condition to
himſelf, which might enforce him to work for his living as honeſt men do,
and not grow ſo fat by the ſweat of other mens brows.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of people I would ſpeak to, in my intended
hopeful Inſtrument of Reformation, is the Profeſſors and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of
the Law; theſe ſhould ſeek to puniſh vice rather then promote it;
<hi>Ergo,</hi> I would deſire them to honor their profeſſion ſo far as
not ſo earneſty defend as they too much do, the Deſtroyers of the publick
Good; that is, the gameſters and Alehouſekeepers and all breakers of penal
Statutes. Well, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115019:24"/>
                  <hi>Semel dictum ſapienti ſat
oſt,</hi> I'll ſay no more, for Iexpect little thanks for this: <hi>R.
T.</hi> Rhadamanthus.</p>
               <p>The third ſort I would adviſe is, ſuch men as take upon
them, or will undertake the proſecution of all penal Laws and Statutes
againſt the contemners and breakers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; which perſons are uſually
called Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters and Informers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be ſure, let me adviſe you
to ſhoot home where you begin let no fair tongues enſnare you; promiſes
nor hopes of reward entice you,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obe caught in their nets;
when, for the lucre of a ſmall Fee (which they al generally ſeek to
enſnare you with) you releaſe them, and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe your ſelves. But, I ſay, draw your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
to the head, and he will flie to the mark: if you proſecute the Law to the
utmoſt without favor or affection, you do that the Law intends you for, and
ſhall being profit and tranquillity to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in general, and to
your ſelves as good members thereof in particular, maugre all opponents;
doubt not but our <hi>Law-makers</hi> and <hi>Keepers,</hi> whom God hath now
raiſed to protect us, wil defend you in the execution of Juſtice: and the
better to direct you, I wil immediately lay <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115019:24"/>down, and
declare to you the heads of the penal ſtatutes, as ſoon as I have done with
my enſuing Articles.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Conſtables and Headboroughs are alſo to preſent
ſuch perſons as do refuſe or neglect to do their duty of watching or
warding.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> Such perſons as divide their Houſes
into ſeveral Tenements; and ſuch as do entertain Inmates, who may be an
annoyance to their Neighbors, or likely to bring charges upon the Pariſh.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Item,</hi> The Defaults of petty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables
Headboroughs, and Tythingmen (theſe are the ſame in Nature, though
dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in Name) for not cauſing Rogues, Vagabonds, and Beggers to be duly
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, puniſhed and paſſed, according to the Statute.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Item,</hi> All maſterleſs men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men living
at their own hands, ſuch as are idle and will not labor, and can give no good
account how they get their living: all ſuſpicious perſons, Whores,
Night-walkers, and mothers of Baſtards, which may be chargeabe to the
Pariſh.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Item.</hi> The Names of ſuch Perſons as
refuſe to take to Apprentice, poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115019:25"/>children, to
Husbandry, and other Callings according to Law.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> All ſuch as neglect to make due
rates and collections for the relief of the poor in every pariſh, and that
cannot give a juſt account of the imployment of the rent and ſtock of the
poor.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Item,</hi> The Defects of the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways and
Bridges, with the names of ſuch as ſhould repair them, and have neglected
or refuſed to do their duty herein.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Item.</hi> Such Scavengers as neglect to do their
office, in cauſing the Streets to be kept clean within their Liberties; and
the names of ſuch perſons as commit common annoyances, by laying of dung,
ſoyl or aſhes in the Street.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> The names of ſuch perſons as
neglect or refuſe to pave the Streets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their houſes, where the
ſaid Streets have uſually been payed.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Such perſons as keep any Hogs in the Streets or
elſewhere to the annoyan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
of the people. <hi>Theſe three laſt are only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for Towns and
Cities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. All ſuch Bakers as put light bread to ſale, and
the weight thereof; and ſuch Brewers as ſell Beer or Ale to unlicenſed 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115019:25"/>Alehouſe-keepers, and ſuch as ingroſs any Corn,
Grain, or any dead Victuals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Compendium of all ſuch penal Statutes as concern
foreſtalling, ingroſſing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grating, Millers. Bakers, Brewers,
Clothwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kers,
Alehouſekeepers, Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Wine without Licenſe, Recuſants, mealmen,
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury and Extortion, ſhould here imediately follow; but in regard we
finde them too prolixo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to
be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Court-Leet, in regard it makes too long a paſſaege to
the Court-Baron; and we not being willing to omit any part thereof, conducible
to the comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n good, ſeeing
we intend this Treatiſe chiefly for the inſtruction of the ignorant in this
moſt needfull knowledge, as well for the plain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man, as for the
benefit of the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> Tyro <hi>in the Law Practiſe; We ſhall
reſerve the addition of the penal Statutes, as an Appendix in the cloſe of
the Book, and proceed to the Court-Baron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now becauſe the Court-Baron is always an adjacent
Neighbor, if not a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with the Court-Leet, I ſhall 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115019:26"/>ſucceſſively give you the form and watters of charge
to be enquired and puniſhed there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Court-Baron holds Plea of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal actions and
treſpaſſes made within the Mannor, where the Tenants are and ought to
have Juſtice at home, and not to be at the charge of a Sute at
<hi>Weſtminster,</hi> for every petty action: where ſometimes the damage is
not three pence, 20 <hi>l.</hi> is ſpent in deciding the Controverſie.</p>
               <p>This Court ought to be kept every three weeks; and to that
intent, the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Rents and Services of his Tenants to do them
Juſtice: and ſome hold their Lands onely, by this ſervice of doing Sute
of Court, and theſe Suiters are the Judges of the Court, though I believe few
Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know a reaſon why
they receive their Quit-Rents; and few Tenants wherefore they pay it: by which
means, the due keeping of theſe Courts, is in many, nay, moſt places
neglected, to the great injury of the people; But a remedy they may have
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord for the non-uſage, or abuſe thereof, which ſhall here
following be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: but to proceed. Firſt, enter the <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115019:26"/>Stile of the Court, which is after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Holſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, ſſ.</hi> The Court-Baron
of <hi>J. W.</hi> held there on <hi>Friday</hi> the 24 of <hi>March</hi> in the
yeer of our Lord, 1656.</p>
               <p>When the Stile of the Court is entred, call the Suiters and
Tenants, entring their appearances and defaults; then make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation,
<hi>That if any one will be eſſoyned or enter any plaint they may come in
and be heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Eſſoyns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Plaints and Pleas be entred,
then impanel the Jury, and ſwear them.</p>
               <p>The Oath is after the ſame manner as the Leet, on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y leaving our theſe words,
<hi>The Council for the Protector,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then after ſilence made, proceed to give in charge theſe
Articles enſuing:</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Jury is to enquire of the Suiters which owe any
Sute to this Court, whether they do attend the Court or no, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the
Defaulters.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Enquire whether any Tenant be dead ſince the laſt
Court, or before, whoſe death is not yet preſented; and preſent the
ſame: and what Lands and Tenements he held of his Mannor at the time of his
death, and by what ſervice; <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115019:27"/>and who is next Heir to the
ſaid Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>If it be Socage-Tenure, the Lord ſhall have his Fealty &amp;
one yeers Rent for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief over and above his yeerly Rent: (I do not mean the
Rent to the value or profits of the Land; though many Lords of Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders,
have much miſtaken themſelves of late, in this caſe, or elſe the
Tenants do too much miſtake themſelves, to the Tenants undoing, when the
fine hath been ſtretcht by the cloak bag-ſtrings of the Lords
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:) and for his relief, the Lord may diſtrain immediately after
the death of his Tenant.</p>
               <p>You ſhall enquire whether any Freehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hath aliened, or
ſold away his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, or any parcel thereof, and preſent it: for he
which bought the Land, before he enter, ought to give notice thereof to the
Lord; and if he bought but a parcel, the Rent ought to be apportioned
accordingly between both parties, according to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Lands
ſold.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Enquire whether any one man hath two ſeveral parcels
of Land holden by ſeveral Titles, &amp; dieth ſeized of the ſame: the
Lord ſhall have two Herriots by his death.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115019:27"/>
               <p>You ſhall alſo enquire whether any Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py holder dieth,
ſeized of any Lands, ſo holden, and preſent it. Alſo, whether any
Copy-holder hath made any Leaſe of his Copy-hold, or otherwiſe aliened or
ſold the ſame, without ſurrender, and preſent it; for its a forfeiture
of his Copy-hold.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo whether any Copy-holder hath made any ſurrender
of his Copy-hold, or any part thereof, ſince the laſt Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, or before,
and preſent it; and into whoſe hands it was made, and to whoſe uſe: for
at every death, or other alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lord is to have a Fyne <hi>(were it
not for this, few Lords would keep any Court at all, though they ought to do
it, to do juſtice to their Tenants;)</hi> and the party into whoſe hands
the ſurrender is made, ought at the next Court to preſent the ſame, and
to certifie the ſurrender into Court to the uſe of the alien, according to
the truſt repoſed in him, on pain of forfeiture of his Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold: and the
party that receiveth the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render is not inveſted in any right in the
eſtate by the ſurrender, unleſs he be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Tenant in Court.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo, if any Tenant of this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115019:28"/>have given any of their Lands into Mortmayn, and preſent
it: if any man give or ſell any Lands to any houſe of Religion, or to any
other which be corporate by the Kings Grant; or if any one make any Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ofment
upon truſt to the uſe of any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houſe, or to the uſe of any
Fraternity or Corporation: this is Mortmain.</p>
               <p>You ſhall alſo enquire whether any Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, for term of life
or yeers, or any Copy-holder of this Lordſhip, hath made any waſte, or
ſuffered any waſte to be done upon their Lands and Ienements, and
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it.</p>
               <p>Waſte is when any Tenant for term of life or yeers, or any
Copy-holder pulleth down any houſe, or cutteth down timber-trees or
ſuffereth any of his Copy-hold-Tenements to decay or fall, or if any of the
Tenants plowup any medow ground or if they ſuffer any wall or pale which was
covered, to be uncovered, by reaſon whereof, the ſame wall or pale doth
fall: or if any Tenant dig coals, chalk, ſand, or make any Myne in his
Ground, it is commitment of waſte.</p>
               <p>But if a Tenant fell Timber to repair Houſes in decay upon his
Copy-hold, and therewith doth repair them, or therewith <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115019:28"/>build a new houſe, or any new building; this is not waſte. But if
he cut down and fell any ſuch Timber, this is waſte. Alſo Copy holders
may cut down Wood to burn upon their Tenements, or to make Reparations without
waſte.</p>
               <p>Enquite alſo, whether any Tenant died, ſeized of any Lands
holden of this Mannor, having no Heir at the time of his death, his Lands
ſhall eſcheat to the Lord.</p>
               <p>None ſhall inherit Lands in Fee-ſimple, unleſs he be Heir,
of the whole blood; and underſtand, that a Baſtard can never be Heir unto
any man; neither can he ever have Heir, but his children of his own body
lawfully begotten: therefore, if any Baſtard die without iſſue, or any
other Tenant die, ſeized without Heirs, preſent it.</p>
               <p>Alſo, if any Tenant ſeized of any Lands or Tenements, was
ejected therefrom by one that had no rightful Title thereunto, and after dies
without Heir. the Lord ſhall have his eſcheat, as well if the Tenant had
died ſeized: <hi>ergo,</hi> enquire thereof, and preſent it.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo, if any Tenant of this Mannor hath been attained
for any Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115019:29"/>Felony, or Murder, for which he had
judgment, although he were afterward delivered, or were burned in the hand: the
Lord hath his Lands by eſcheat: or if any one hath abjured the Land or be
outlawed for any Treaſon, Felony, or Murder, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it: for the Lord
ſhall have his Land by eſcheat.</p>
               <p>You are alſo to enquire, if there be any rents, cuſtoms, or
Services withdrawn from the Lordſhip which are due, and of right ought to be
done thereunto; and what Rights, Cuſtomes, and Services they are, by whom
withdrawn, and where the Land lies out of which they be due, and who holds the
ſame, and preſent it.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo, whether any Waif or Stray was or is within this
Lordſhip; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord be anſwered of the ſame; and if not,
preſent by whom they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; and if any Herriot be conveyed away or
concealed, preſent it, and by whom.</p>
               <q> 
                  <l>And here it will not be any digreſsion</l> 
                  <l>to tell you what a Waif and Stray is.</l>
               </q>
               <p>A Waif is if a Thing being purſued, or <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115019:29"/>otherwiſe to eaſe himſelf of his burden, doth leave and
forſake his goods, which he hath ſtollen, or any part of them; ſuch Goods
are called Waifs: and the chief Lord ſhall have the Goods ſo waived,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Owner of them, do make freſh ſuit after the Thief, and attach
him for ſtealing the ſaid Goods; in ſuch caſs he ſhall have his Goods
again, though they be waived; but then he muſt ſue an appeal, or elſe
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Thief to be convicted at his Sute, 21 <hi>H. cap.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>An Eſtray is, if any Beaſt be found in the Lordſhip, and
no man know the Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof, they ſhall be ſeized to the uſe of the
King, unleſs the Lord have them by Grant or Preſcription, if the Owner do
not claim the ſame within a year and a day after the Lord hath cauſed
Proclamation to be made in the next Markets, and in the Church, according to
the Statute.</p>
               <p>Alſo enquire, whether any perſon hath made any Reſcous
againſt the Lord or his Officers within the Mannor, and preſent it: That if
the Lord come to diſtrain for his Rent, and the Tenant reſiſt him, that
he cannot diſtrain, this is a reſcue; or, if Beaſts diſtrained run into
the houſe of the <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115019:30"/>Owner, and the Diſtrainer prays them
to be delivered to him, and the poſſeſſors will not deliver them, it is
a Reſcue.</p>
               <p>You are likewiſe to enquire of, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all
pound-breaches; whether any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath broken the Lord's Pound, that is, to
have taken away any diſtreſs put therein: if the Lord do diſtrain for
Rent or ſervice behinde, he may impound the diſtreſs either in a common
Pound or in his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ground,
if he will, or in his Neighbors Ground, by the Licenſe of his Neighbor: and
any place in which the Lord doth impound, is the Lord's Pound: but if any other
perſon do impound any Cattle in his own Pound or his Neighbors, he ought to
give notice thereof to the other party, that is, to the Owner of them, that he
may give them meat if he will; and then if the Beaſt die for want of food, he
that was diſtrained ſhall be at the loſs, and he that did diſtrain, may
diſtrain again for the ſame Rent or Duty,</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo, if any Inhabitant have overcharged the Common,
or High-ways, or common Fields, by putting therein more Cattel then they ought
to keep, or before the days agreed upon, and preſent it; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115019:30"/>the Lord
may diſtrain the Surpluſſage, Damage Feiſant.</p>
               <p>There may alſo be made certain Orders by the Inhabitants, one
among another, which none may break under ſuch penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as they agree upon
between themſelves.</p>
               <p>Alſo you ſhall enquire, whether any perſons have digged
any Holes or Pits in the High-wayes, or whether any uſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to break
Hedges, or ſuffer any Hoggs to go unringed or unyoked, to the annoyance, of
their Neighbors, and preſent the ſame.</p>
               <p>Enquire likewiſe whether any perſon hath ſtopped any
Water-courſe, Way, Ditch, Path or Stile, or turned any of them out of their
way, and preſent it; have a care in this caſe you preſentno man
malitiouſly; a foot or two to ſtep about its, not ſo great damage to any
as to cauſe a ſuite more then the value of the land, as ſome have done,
and after repented too late.</p>
               <p>Alſo, whether any Tenant hath made any incroachment upon any
of the Lord's Land, Meadow, Paſture, Wood, Heath, or other vacant Ground,
without the Lord's leave; or hath ſet his Hedge or Pale, beyond his due
bounds, &amp; preſent the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115019:31"/>
               <p>Alſo enquire, whether any perſon hath plowed up, or removed
any Meerbanks, Banks, or removed any Bounds or Limits between one piece of Land
and another, and preſent it.</p>
               <p>Alſo, you ſhall enquire whether any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth detain or
keep away, or detain any of the Lords Court-Rollsor Evidences and preſent the
ſame.</p>
               <p>Alſo if any perſon have Hunted, Hawked, Fiſhed or Fowled
in the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s Warren, and
preſent it.</p>
               <p>Alſo, you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll enquire, if any perſons have taken any Eggs of the Lord's
Swans out of their Neſts, and preſent their names.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo if any treſpaſs be done in any of the Lord's
Liberties, either in his Corn Graſs, Meadows, Paſture, Woods, Waters,
Ponds, or Hedges; or take, or deſtroy any Aiery of Haws, and preſent the
ſame.</p>
               <p>Enquire alſo, if any Land be incloſed that ought to lye
open, without the licenſe of the Lord and other Freeholders, and preſent
the ſame, that the Tenants of the Mannor may not loſe their Common
thereof.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115019:31"/>
               <p>Enquire alſo, whether any Tenant for life or term of yeers,
hath let any greater or longer eſtate in his Lands or Tenements then he hath
therein; it is a forſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ture of their Eſtates.</p>
               <p>Enquire laſtly, if all the Defaults and Plaints preſented at
the laſt Court, be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently and duly amended: and whether all the
Orders and Rules made heretofore concerning this Mannor, be obſerved and
kept, and preſent it; and if you know any thing more fitting to be, or that
ought to be preſented for the Lords profit, or your own common good,
diligently enquire thereof, as you are in con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cience bound, according to the Oaths you have
taken, and are obliged to both by God and man: ſtudying as much as in you
lits, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good and welfare on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of another: and to that end, of all matters given you in charge,
and here to be enquired of, make a true preſentment, diſtinctly and plainly
without malice, in ſpeaking more then is true, or favor in concealing any one
that is culpable, againſt the truth.</p>
               <p>The form and manner of proceeding in perſonal Actions both in
the Court-Leet, Court-Baron, (&amp; alſo the hundred Courts, 
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115019:32"/>which is alſo a Court held generally every three weeks,
to hold plea in perſonal Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where the debt or damages exceed not 40
<hi>s.</hi> by the Sheriff in many places, or by his Steward, if the King be
Lord thereof; or if it be a particular Lord, by his Steward for the whole
Hundred:) I ſay, the Proceſs of theſe Courts, is, Summons, Attachment and
Diſtreſs, to be directed by Precept from the Steward of the Court to the
Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff of the ſame, where it lies in the choice of the Plaintiff either to
ſummon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, or attach his Goods; which he muſt put in Bayl unto,
to appear at the next Court to anſwer the Defendant, which is uſual in
treſpaſs: but in debt, onely a Summons without bayl; a laudable way of
granting out Proceſs in all Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, coming neereſt the
purity of the original and ancient practice of the Laws of this Nation.</p>
               <p>And if the Original in the Court of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas were only
uſed, and the <hi>Capiat</hi> taken away, or rather indeed a
<hi>Sub-poena</hi> only in all Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, &amp; an Attachment to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in caſe of Contempt, how much
vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous charge &amp; trouble would the people of the Nation be freed from,
and their Eſtates <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115019:32"/>and perſons ſaved from the
devouring clutches of thoſe ravenous Wolves, the Catch-poles and Sergeants,
to which honeſt men are often enforced ſubjects; when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, nay, moſt
often, leſs charge would end the difference then theſe men expoſe both
parties unto: and for which, both Plaintiff and Defendant ſit down
loſers.</p>
               <p>But becauſe it is our earneſt deſire to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue peace as
much as is poſſible with all men we, ſhall here lay down a method of
keeping a Court of Survey; which if all Lords and Tenants would, as if they
will, with a little charge they may, joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and perfectly obſerve,
the Right and Propriety of every man might be known and regiſtred amongſt
them, and thereby many tedious, conſuming, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Title-Sutes at Law,
avoided; for by this means, every one might know his own; and he that will not
therewith be content, deſerves nothing.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115019:33"/>
               <p>The manner, form, and method of keeping a Court of Survey for
the ſurveying, ſetting forth, Butting, deſcribing and bounding of any
Mannor or Town; with the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Tenures belonging to the ſame. With the
form of making a Terrar or Field-book, and the Articles to be given in charge
to the Jury, in a Court of Survey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Articles to be enquired of and given in charge in a Court of
Survey holden for the Mannor of A. in the Pariſh of H. in the County of N:
the</hi> 8 <hi>day of</hi> May, 1656.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN primis.</hi> Who have, or are ſuſpected to have, or
keep back any of the Lord's Evdences, Court-Rolls, Rentals, Books of Survey,
Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rars or Writings whats
ſoever, concerning the ſaid Mannor, and who have been Stewards of the
ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor within the time of your remembrance.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115019:33"/>
               <p>Note, if there be a Survey holden for two Mannors or more, at
one time; then ſay, inſtead of <hi>Mannor, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors. And the ſaid
Mannors, or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Item</hi> That you inform what Limits and Bounds
belong to the ſaid Mannors; and what Lords are bounding or border<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
therupon, or whether they do ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lenge intrude or encroach upon the Lands of the Lords of the ſaid
Mannors.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Item,</hi> That you ſet forth the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Lands
and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enements, within the
ſaid Mannors from the Copy-hold, cuſtomary and demeaſne Lands of the
ſaid Mannors, and either of them, or any other Mannor, and who are the
Free-hold Tenants or Occupiers therof, and what are their names and what
Free<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hold Rent do they
ſeverally pay to the Lord of the ſaid Mannors for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Item,</hi> What alienations, tranſmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or
alterations have been made of any Free-hold Lands within or belonging to the
ſaid Mannors or either of them, and what is due to the Lord upon any ſuch
ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enation, tranſmutation or alteration.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115019:34"/>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Item,</hi> What Houſes or Tenements of Freehold
are now ſtanding, or have been decayed within the ſaid Mannors: by whom and
when were they ſo decayed; what Laws do or heretofore did belong to every
ſuch Houſe or Tenement; and what Lands have been ſold from the ſaid
Houſes or Tenements, and to whom.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Item,</hi> What Tenements or Cottages are lately
built within the ſaid Manors, that are holden at will, or ſufferance, or by
Copy of Court-Roll of the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, or either of them, or any other
Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and who be the owners or occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof, and what Rents and
Services do they yield and pay for the ſame, and what Laws do belong to every
ſuch Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Cottage, and how long ſince have any ſuch Tenements or
Cortages been built, and what Commonage do they challenge for the ſame, and
by what right, and what is the name of ſuch Common or Commons they challenge
Commonage in.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Item,</hi> How many Copy-hold or Cuſtomary
Tenants, are within or belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid Mannors, and either of them and
what be their ſeveral names, and what <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115019:34"/>Meſſuages,
Land<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Tenements, or Hered
i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments, hath every ſuch Copy-holder or Cuſtomary Tenant; what are their
ſeveral quantities and yearly values, where do they lie, and how they are
abuttalled, and by what Rents and Services doth every ſuch Copy-holder hold
the ſame.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Item,</hi> Whether any of the Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders within
the ſaid Mannors have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed, bargained or ſold any of their Copy-hold
Lands or Tenements to any Free-holder, and what are ſuch Lands and Tenements
ſo bargained, exchanged and ſold, yearly worth, and where do they lie.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Item,</hi> Whether any Copy-hold or Cnſtomary
Tenant of the ſaid Mannors or either of them, hath let or ſet for any time
or term of years, his Copy-hold, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary Lands or Tenemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, or any part thereof, without
the Lords licenſe, and whether any enjoy any Copy-hold, or Cuſtomary Lands,
not having a Copy or Grant thereof immediately from the Lord of the ſaid
Mannors, and what be their names, and the yearly value thereof.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Item,</hi> What Lands, Tenements, Rents, Services
or Hereditaments, within, <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115019:35"/>or belonging to the ſaid
Mannors, are withholden, concealed, or ſubſtracted from the Lord of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſaid Mannors, by whom,
and when, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Item,</hi> What Heath-Grounds, Sheep courſes or
Sheep-walks are within or belonging to the ſaid Mannors, how are they
ſcituated, ſet forth, or bounded; and how many Acres, do every ſuch Heath
Sheep courſe or Sheep-walk contain, by meaſure or eſtimation; and how
many Sheep will the ſame yearly maintain and keep, and what other Priviledges
or Cuſtomary Feede do belong to the ſaid Sheeps-courſe or Sheeps-walk;
and where do the ſame lie; and at what time or times in the year is the
ſaid Priviledge and Feede to be taken, and what is the yearly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the
ſaid Sheep-walk or Sheeps-courſe.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Item,</hi> Whether any can or do juſtly claim
or hold any Land that lies within the ſaid Heath-Grounds, Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe or
Sheeps walks and by what right do they hold or claim the ſame, and how much
Land have every ſuch Land-holder, and whether have they not other Lands of
the Lord of the ſaid Mannors in Leiu or <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115019:35"/>exchange thereof,
and where do the ſaid exchanged Lands ſeverally lie: and how are they
abuttalled and bounded, and what be the ſeveral Names of the Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers of
ſuch Lands, and their ſeveral quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities.</p>
               <p n="13">1. <hi>Item,</hi> What Commons, commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Grounds,
waſte and vacant Grounds are within and belonging to the ſame Mannors, and
what be their ſeveral names: how are they ſcituated, metred, let forth or
bounded; and how many Acres doe every ſuch Common, commonable Grounds,
waſte and vacant Grounds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by eſtimation, and who can and do
juſtly claim or pretend to have any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Feede in the ſaid commonable
Grounds, waſte and vacant Grounds, and what be their ſeveral names.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Item,</hi> What Incloſures and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments
have been made at any time heretofore, and now being in, upon, or out of the
ſaid Commons, commonable Grounds, waſte and vacant Grounds, by whom, where,
and when were they made, and what quantity, and by what warrant or right they
did, or do hold the ſame.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Item,</hi> What plantings or Trees is 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115019:36"/>now, and have been hertofore ſet or grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon any of
the Commons belonging to the ſaid Mannors or either of them, by whom they
have been ſo ſet or planted, and what be their names that challenge the
ſame as helonging to their Houſes or Tenements, and what be the names of
ſuch Houſes or Tenements, and how far off are the ſaid Plantings or Trees
planted or growing from the ſaid Houſes or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and what number of
Plantings or trees do they ſeverally challenge to belong to their ſaid
Houſes or Tenements, and by what right; and who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h lopred, felled, ſold or converted to their
own uſe any ſuch Plantings or Trees, and for how much do they or any of
them hold the ſame.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Item,</hi> What dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſne Lands are belonging to the ſaid Mannors,
and either of them, and where do they ſeverally lie, and how are they
abuttalled, and what be their ſeveral quantities and qualities and their
yearly value; and what be the names of them that have them in Farm, exchange or
Occupation; and for what Rent and term, or for what cauſe do they ſeverally
hold the ſame.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Item,</hi> What Liberties, Freedoms 
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115019:36"/>Frankchiſes, and other preheminences and royalties do
belong or appertain to the ſaid Mannors, what are the ſame, and what profit
may be yearly, or otherwiſe made or raiſed by the Lord thereby.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Laſtly, to enquire and certifie who ſhal neglect
or refuſe to bring in and ſhew forth their Deeds or their Evidences of all
their Free-hold Lands and Tenements within the ſaid Manor, together with all
their Copies or Court Rolls of all ſuch Lands as they ſeverally hold by
Copy of Court-Roll of the Mannors aforeſaid, for the better ſetting forth
and diſtinguiſhing of the ſaid Lands accordingly, whereby the Survey of
the ſaid Mannors may be made the more perfect.</p>
               <p>The manner of making the Terrar or Field-Book, may be thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A general Survey and Field book taken at H. in the County of
S. holden for the Mannors of G. and H. by R. T Steward and Survayor of the
ſame. the</hi> 10 <hi>day of M</hi> 1656. <hi>wherein all the Meſſuages,
Lands, and Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the ſaid Mannors, are ſet <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115019:37"/>forth, butted and bounded. The Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure how all ſuch Lands are
holden, and who be the right Owners thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then begin at what part of the Town you pleaſe, ſo go
through, ſetting down every parcel of Land, Meſſuage or Tenement
diſtinctly, abutting and bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: and at laſt, ſet down the Tenure
and Title of the Owner or Inheritor, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his evidence for the ſame:
as thus; if you begin at the Mannor houſe, then begin your Survey Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. B. <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Lord of the Mannor of H.</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>holdeth one Meſſuage or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor houſe; being the ſcite of
the Manner aforeſaid, in his Demeaſne as of Fee, together with Barns,
Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Dove houſe, Orchards, Garden,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>abutting and
bounding the ſame exactly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then proceed to the next land as you go, whether Eaſt or
Weſt: if, Eaſt, then thus.</p>
               <p>A. S. <hi>holdeth next, and more Eaſt, <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115019:37"/>twenty Acres of Arable Land, abut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as it
lies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by Copy of Court Roll:</hi> ut patet per Cop. ſuam de
Rotulis Curiae,</p>
               <p>If it be Free hold of Inheritance, then ſay;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. S. holdeth of the ſame Mannor, one Free-Tenement,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>abutting it exactly and putting down his Title and Tenure;
according to his Evidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Lords of Mannors, and Tenants in their ſeveral
Pariſhes and Townſhips would but joyn together, with a little charge, they
might have Books of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey made of their ſeveral Mannors, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in each mans
Propriety might be recorded and known: and this being done, but once in an age,
or by every ſucceeding Lord, his Tenants and himſelf might live in amity
and tranquillity; and many chargeable and vexatious Law-Suits, to the undoing
of thouſands, avoided: and people might quietly follow their Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at
home, and not the promotion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others, by the ruine of themſelves: But <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115019:38"/>probably the Obſtructors of Peace will give me ſmall thanks for
this. Oh <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feur Self-ends</hi> and <hi>Avidus!</hi> when wilt thou
depart from us? <hi>R. T. Pacis dulcis Amator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Acording to promiſe, I ſhall proceed to declare the manner
of proceeding in ſome inferiour Courts of Record of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; but
declaring them fitter Ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ects of Reformation then Practice; hey were indeed originally
inſtituted for the more ſpeedy adminiſtration of Juſtice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
party and party, in their Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but are now, by the corruption of
time, become Inſtruments of vexation and injury: and becauſe they are
ſeated in the <hi>Metropolis,</hi> I ſhall firſt begin with the Sheriffs
Court of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is holden at the <hi>Guild hall</hi> for the City of
<hi>London,</hi> two Court-days for one <hi>Compter,</hi> holden before one of
the Sheriffs; and two Court-days for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Compter,</hi> before the
other Sheriff in every week: holding Plea in all perſonal Actions <hi>ad
infinitum.</hi> Their Practice in both Courts, differs neither in manner, nor 
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115019:38"/>form nor ſubſtance; but the beginning of their
proceeding, I mean, the levying of their Plaints is the moſt unjuſt and
illegal, both in the eye of the Law, and of all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional people of any Court
in the World.</p>
               <p>For indeed the blame of all Courts, is, that they do not
iſſue out Summons, and take ſufficient Pledges to proſecute upon the
Return of the Summons, as the Law o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally intends, before the awarding of
any <hi>Capias,</hi> for arreſting the Body of the Defendant: but return an
Original of courſe (as they call it) ſometimes, and ſometimes not at all;
putting <hi>John Doe</hi> and <hi>Richard Roe,</hi> for pledges to proſecute;
whereas indeed, there ought to be a due Summons firſt returned, and Pledges,
that is ſufficient Sureties, That if the Plantiff do not proſecute, or be
overthrown in his Action, the Defendant ſhall be ſatisfied his coſts and
damages for his unjuſt trouble, charge and vexation.</p>
               <p>But the Practice of theſe Sheriffs Courts is ſo far from
this, that they make out no Proceſs nor Precept at all for to warrant their
Arreſt. But they have a Book in their Office at the <hi>Compter</hi>-gates,
wherein they enter the Actions, that is, the Plantiffs and <pb n="68" facs="tcp:115019:39"/>Defendants Names, and the Debt or Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; and that is all: And this
is moſt often done after the party is arreſted and in Priſon: for if two
of their Varlets meet a man in the ſtreet, minding to make a prey of him; for
which they continually lurk, they immediatly ſeize on him, if they know but
any perſon he hath any dealing with, be the Caſe right or wrong, they
preſently drag him to the <hi>Compter,</hi> or their petty Goals at next
door, and then run and enter againſt him what Actions they pleaſe, in the
Name of any Man. And at the next Court-day, the Defendant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, after two
or three days impriſonment, may obtain a Non-Sute; and ſhall have adjudged
him 7 <hi>s.</hi> 2 <hi>d.</hi> for his Charges, which is not the tythe
thereof: and that he may look for, if he can tell of who: or any man
whatſoever, that hath any envy in his breaſt, which there are few that
want, may come and enter an Action againſt any man he's minded to do a
miſchief unto, and keep him in Priſon (at 8 <hi>d. per</hi> week charges to
the Knave) as long as he lives. And their way of taking of Pledges of
proſecuting, is thus: To demand of the Plantiff, or he that enters the
Plaint, where <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115019:39"/>he lives: if he ſay in
<hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> then then they enter Pledges to proſecute, <hi>John
Fleet, Richard Street;</hi> if in <hi>Common-Garden,</hi> then Pledges,
<hi>&amp;c. John Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Richard Garden:</hi> according to the place the party
names, though no ſuch man be.</p>
               <p>And it is a great oppreſſion to Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people, who are thus
ſnapt up by irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Proceedings. This is not to expedite Juſtice, but to
diſgrace the Law, and wrong the Commonalty. By this means, I have known many
utterly undone; and ſome have lain in Priſon five weeks upon this account,
and never knew, heard of, nor could never find out his Adverſaries.</p>
               <p>And then, after this he hath non-ſuited their Actions, entred
over and over again, they take a Preſident from a worſe then this, that I
muſt take ſo much leave, as plainly to ſpeak of; that is, the Court of
Upper-Bench, from whence iſſues a Writ, called a <hi>Latitat;</hi> or in
the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> A Bill of <hi>Middleſex:</hi> and uppon
the ſuppoſition of one of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, though never any ſuch thing
be, they reward a <hi>Latitat</hi> into all Counties, to take the Defendant,
without naming the <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115019:40"/>cauſe, onely Treſpaſs, be it what
it will be; upon which, if he cannot put in bayl, he ſhall lie in Priſon
three Terms; which ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with the Vacations to boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, is above three quarters of a yeer: and then if
the Plantiff declare not, he may obtain his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty by a
<hi>Superſedeas,</hi> if he hath money to purchaſe it: but not a farthing
coſts, or any remedy againſt the party that injured him; by this wicked
practice, many a poor Soule miſerably endes his dayes in New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate.</p>
               <p>And if a man be arreſted by a <hi>Latitat</hi> or Bill of
<hi>Middleſex,</hi> and the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aintiff never declare after he hath put in Bayl, he ſhall not
have any coſts, but only a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuite or a Diſcontinuance as they call
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Defendant
appear in perſon, and that is hardly worth his while. This I make bold here
to mention, becauſe it is a G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ievance cries loud for Redreſs, and ſo doth the City-Court too:
for can it ſeem reaſonable that any man ſhould be arreſted and
impriſoned he knows not why nor wherefore? and moſt times irregularly; the
Serjeants having the advantage to do it without Warrant, or any Precept or
Proceſs to be ſhown; oftentimes, nay, <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115019:40"/>moſt commonly
impriſon the Defendant without any Action entred againſt him. This Practice
was abhorred by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens: and then is it not a ſhame it ſhould be
tolerated by Chriſtians?</p>
               <p>But after the Arreſt, the Defendant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing by Attorney,
the Plantiffs Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney declares if cauſe be; and then they fairly proceed to
Trial, according to the ſubſtance of the Proceeding of the Upper-Bench,
though different in form: and to the Defendant, if he be a Free-man in caſe
of debt, is allowed four Defaults, by which time he may make his peace if he be
wiſe.</p>
               <p>And by the way give me leave to tell you, that I have read, and
I am ſure 'tis reaſonable, That it is not lawful for a Citizen, or one
living in a Corporation to arreſt any ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anger that inhabits in another Country, into one
of theſe Courts; but by Proceſs from above: for theſe Courts had their
Authority granted them originally from the King for their eaſe, and the more
eaſie diſpatch of Juſtice between one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their ſeveral
Franchiſes: for as the Forraigner hath no benefit by their Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe; ſo
ought he not to be impleaded in their Courts. Beſides, a great
diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagedies <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115019:41"/>upon the ſtranger being far from
home, and diſtant from Friends, is too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten enforced to purchaſe his
Liberty by an unjuſt Compoſition.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a Court holden before the Major and Alderman in
the <hi>Guild-hall</hi> of the ſaid City, unto which the Sheriffs Court is
ſubject by removal, and both of them to a <hi>Habeas Corpur</hi> out of the
Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bench or Common Pleas, if the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be not under five pounds; and if
it be, then the Defendant may cauſe another Action to be entred againſt
him, at the Sute of any perſon he will name, which is above 5 <hi>l</hi> and
remove both together.</p>
               <p>There is alſo another Court of Equity, held between one
Freeman and another in the ſaid City, wherein they regularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by
Summons in all Debts not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 40 <hi>s.</hi> and pity it is that the
Authority of that Court extends no higher.</p>
               <p>Thus by the head, you may gueſs at the whole Body; I mean, the
Proceedings of all Corporations: for ſetting the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or
Proceſs aſide, when they come to declare, they do generally in their
Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions imitate the Bills and Declarations of the Upper Bench.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115019:41"/>
               <p>I would be larger, but I proceed to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things here more
aimed at: only by the way let me deſire the Stewards and Judges of all ſuch
Courts, to be careful in amending what Er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors they finde have through the ruſt of
Antiquity, crept in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: endeavoring as much as they can the eaſe of
the Subject, and equal Right to all.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115019:42"/>
            <head>Certain Queſtions and Caſes in LAW, Reſolved.</head>
            <p n="1">1. JOHN Doe <hi>ſurrendred to his Wife certain Copy-hold
Land of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance to her, and to the Heirs of their two Bodides, to be
begotten; and for default of ſuch iſſue to the right heirs of the
ſaid</hi> John Doe; <hi>but in the ſaid ſurrender, doth not expreſs
that he gives it to her for her Joynture, althugh it was his intent ſhe
ſhould have ne other Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whether is this a Joynture or not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſaid</hi> John Doe <hi>died without Will, his
Wife adminiſtred, and there was certain Timber felled for the repair of a
Copy-hold belonging to the Heir, which the Praiſers refuſe to put into the
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventory, <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115019:42"/>for the reaſon aforeſaid. This Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
marries again, and her Husband takes away the Timber ſo felled from off the
Lands belonaing to the ſaid Heir: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this Felony or not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Her ſaid Husband is the Lord of the Mannor, and
doth detain and keep cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Writings from the Heir of the ſaid Deceaſed,
refuſing to keep any Court where the Heir ſhould be admitted Tenant to
certain Copy-hold Land lying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Manor; but doth deſtrain for
Quit-Rent upon the Land belonging to the Heir, refuſing to deliver the Heir
his Writings, or ſhew any Title he hath to the Quit-Rent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether the aforenamed Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render being accepted and
taken, doth not barr the woman to have any Dowry either in Fee or Copy-hold
Lands, after her deceaſed Husband, although the Cuſtom Book of that place
where the Copy hold lieth, renders the Widdow of the Deceaſed the third part
of tho Lands, that her Husband died ſeized of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>What ſorts of Wood is accounted Timber by the Law;
and whether the <pb n="76" facs="tcp:115019:43"/>Woman by vertue of the aforenamed
Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, can cut and ſell any manner of Woods growing upon the ſaid
ſurrendred Lands, to make a waſte and ſpoil: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Land
reſtrains her but to cut for neceſſary uſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Whether the Widow of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed in her
Widdowhood letting a Leeſe</hi> Parole <hi>for five yeares of her
ſurrendred Land, contrary to the Cuſtome, ought not to make good the ſaid
Leaſe</hi> Parole <hi>to the Tenant, becauſe he ſhall be much damnified
if he enjoy not the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>If a man taken with an Execution for Debt by the
Sheriffs Bayliffs, and the ſaid Bayliffs ſuffer him to make an eſcape,
and the Creditor reneweth not the Execution in two or three yeares after,
whether may he afterward bring his Action againſt the Sheriff or the
Debtor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>We deſire to know what penalty is to be laid upon
the Lord of the Manner which ought to keep a Court-Leet once a year, and doth
not, and to whom the penalty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>How Lords of Mannors do hold their Lordſhips and
Mannors, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb n="77" facs="tcp:115019:43"/>they pay any Rent therefore or
no?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>If Lord of a Mannor commit Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, who is to have
the forfeiture of his Royalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Reſolution of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Queſtions.</head>
               <p>To the firſt: A Joynture of a Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold doth not bar Dower;
for that at the common Law it it did not; and by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Uſes the
Joynture muſt be of Lands at the common Law; and whereof Uſes might be
raiſed, which holds in neither in Copy-holds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not Felony, but the Lord of the Mannor may have
an Action of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs again the ſaid Husband; or the Heir may have an
Action upon the caſe againſt him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Heir may ſue him at common Law for detaining of
his Writings: and touching the diſtreſs for Quit-Rents, let the Tenant
bring a Replevin, and the Lord upon his Avowry muſt ſhew his Title.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115019:44"/>
               <p n="4">4. The Statute of Joyntures doth not extend to Copy-holds
for the Reaſons gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the firſt Queſtion; and therefore that Statute
is no bar.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Elm, Oak and Aſh are accounted Timber in Law: and
Beech in Countries barren of Wood: the Law reſtrains any Copy-holder to fell
Wood or Trees but for neceſſary uſes, unleſs the cuſtom war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it
otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Leaſe <hi>Parole</hi> for five years not
warranted by the Cuſtom is a forfeiture of the Widdows eſtate, if the Lord
take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereof; if the Lord ſo do, the Leſſee hath no
remedy.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Againſt the Debtor he can have no Action of Debt; for
his Action was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by he Execution: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two or three years he
may bring an Action of Debt againſt the Sheriff.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> lieth for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſer or
abuſer of a Franchiſe. The penalty is the Seizer of the Leer.</p>
               <p n="9">9. All Lordſhips and Mannors were holden before theſe
times <hi>meditate</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditate</hi> from the King by accuſtomed
or reſerved ſervices.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:115019:44"/>
               <p n="10">10. If he hold of the King, the King if of a meaſne
Lord, that Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Caſes reſolved touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wills.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head type="sub">What perſons are by the Law to make a Will or
Teſtament, and who not.</head>
                  <p>A Perſon our-lawed for Felony can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make a Will; but if a
man be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed only in Perſonal Actions, he may make a Teſtament of his
Lands, but not of his Goods. The ſame Law is of a man at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of a
<hi>Praemunire,</hi> but not of a man excommunicated.</p>
                  <p>An Infant making a Will of his Land within age, and dieth
after he cometh at full age, not revoking this Will, it is not a good Will.</p>
                  <p>A woman ſeized of Land and marrieth, and afterwards maketh a
Will of it: this is not good.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115019:45"/>
                  <p>A Lunatick being of ſound memory, maketh his Will and
becometh Lunatick; and afterwards comes to his underſtanding and dies: this
is not a good Will.</p>
                  <p>A man ſpeechleſs, or one born deaf and dumb, may make a
Will by ſignes.</p>
                  <p>A man being of a ſound memory, makes his Will, and
afterwards becomes mad, and ſo dies: this is not a good Will:</p>
                  <p>A man who hath a Wife not divorced taketh another Wife who is
an Inheritrix; ſhe cannot make a Will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What is a good Will, and what not; and what ſhall be a
Revocation, and what not.</head>
                  <p>A Will without naming any Executor is good for Lands, but not
for Goods</p>
                  <p>A Will wanting date is good, if made after the 20 day of
<hi>July</hi> 1540.</p>
                  <p>A Will without ſealing or ſubſcribing if it be made in
writing in the life time of the Teſtator, although it be never proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Ordinary.</p>
                  <p>A Will Nuncupative is not good for Land.</p>
                  <p>Two men ſeverally ſeized of Land, <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115019:45"/>make
a joynt Teſtament of their Lands: this is good.</p>
                  <p>A man is making his Will, and hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed parcel of his
Land; and before the finiſhing thereof, he dieth: the Wil is good, for ſo
much as is deviſed.</p>
                  <p>If a man appoint by his Will, that his Land ſhall be fold to
pay his debts, and ſheweth not by whom; the Will is good, and ſhal be
performed by the Executors or adminiſtrators.</p>
                  <p>If a man makes a Will of land that is not his own, and after
purchaſe the ſame land and die: this is not a good Will.</p>
                  <p>Alſo if a man makes a Will of his land, and after alien this
land, and afterwards repurchaſeth it again, this not a good Will.</p>
                  <p>A Woman makes a Will of her Land, and after takes a husband,
who hath iſſue; the husband and the Wife both die: this is not a good
Will.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a Will, and afterwards makes a new Will; and after
in his bed dying, ſaith that his firſt Will ſhall be his laſt Will,
this is good.</p>
                  <p>A man makes his Will in writing, and after giveth divers
Legacies to ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115019:46"/>then after by word
revoketh all but one: this is a good Revocation of all but that one.</p>
                  <p>If any man gives land by Will to one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Fee, and
afterwards giveth the ſame land to another perſon by another Wil but for
term of life: this is a Revocation of the firſt Will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What things are deviſeable or may be deviſed.</head>
                  <p>If any man be ſeized of lands deviſeable, and thereupon
buildeth; the houſe or buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding may be deviſed. So likewiſe may a Rent
charge created <hi>de novo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A man ſeized in right of his wife, and granteth parcel of
his land to one, and after deviſeth the reſidue to another: this is
good.</p>
                  <p>If a Farmer of land not deviſeable, erect and fix a Furnace
in the midſt of the houſe in the land, he may deviſe this Furnace.</p>
                  <p>A Tenant in Fee-ſimple or Fee-tail, may deviſe the Corn,
although the land be not deviſeable: but trees he cannot.</p>
                  <p>A man ſeized of a Mill, may deviſe the runner-ſtone- but
not the under-ſtone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a man have an annuity to him and his <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115019:46"/>heirs, he cannot deviſe this annuity: but if it be an annuity for
term of years, he may.</p>
                  <p>If a husband die, having before deviſed Corn upon his wives
land, it is good, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were ſown before the Marriage or after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What words ſhall make Fee-ſimple lands, and what
not.</head>
                  <p>Land given to a man to hold to him and his heirs, with
Warranty of the land to him and his heirs, this is a good Feeſimple.</p>
                  <p>Land deviſed to a man by Will, by theſe words, <hi>To do
with it at his pleaſure;</hi> this is a good Fee ſimple.</p>
                  <p>Lands given to a man, to hold to him in Fee-ſimple, and
livery made to him and his heirs according to the form and effect of the deed;
it maketh Feeſimple.</p>
                  <p>Land given to one for term of life, and livery and ſeiſin
made to him and his heirs, according to the form and effect of the Deed; this
is not Fee-ſimple.</p>
                  <p>A man ſeized in Fee-ſimple, grants <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſtatum
ſuum,</hi> his whole eſtate; <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> bend'</hi> to the grantee and his heirs, and maketh livery
according to the Deed: this is Fee-ſimple.</p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115019:47"/>
                  <p>A man leavyeth a Fine <hi>ſur Connuzance de droit come
ceo</hi> &amp;c. The Conuſee, that is, he to whom the Fine is granted, hath
Fee-ſimple.</p>
                  <p>Two Coparceners in Fee ſimple make partition; and for
equality of partition, a Rent is aſſigned out of one part to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
without any other words: the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne hath the Fee-ſimple in the
Rent.</p>
                  <p>Land is given by Deed, the <hi>Habendum ſibi &amp;
haeredibus ſuis, vel de corpore ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> to him and his heirs, or heirs of his body; this is not
Fee-ſimple: But if the <hi>Habendum</hi> were <hi>ſibi &amp; haeredibus
ſuis, vel ſmis aſſignatis,</hi> to him and his heirs or
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a Leaſe of two acres of Land for life the
remainder of one of them (without ſhewing which) to a ſingle wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Fee:
ſhe taketh a husband, and after the Leſſee is impleaded in a <hi>Praecipe
quod reddat</hi> of one of the acres, and prayeth ayde of the husband and wife,
as of them in remainder: they joyn in aid <hi>gratis,</hi> and cannot bar the
demandant, whereby he recovereth. The husband dies, the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee dies; the
Wife hath the fee-ſimple in the other acre.</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115019:47"/>
                  <p>Tenant in tayl enfeoffeth his brother, Recovery is had
againſt him by erroneous Judgment: the Tenant in tail hath iſſue, and
dieth; the iſſue within age; the brother dieth without iſſue: the
iſſue in tail being his heir within age, reſerveth the Judgment by error,
and enters; he hath fee ſimple.</p>
                  <p>A Leaſe is made to the husband and wife by Deed, <hi>pro
termino vitae ſuae. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum eis pro termino vitae,</hi> to have to them for
term of life of the wife: ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the husband continues in
poſſeſſion, he hath fee-ſimple.</p>
                  <p>A Leaſe is made to a woman for term of years, upon
condition, that if ſhe have iſſue within the term, that ſhe ſhal have
fee; the Leſſor and Leſſee inter-marry, and have iſſue within the
term, and the husband di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; the term expireth, and the wife conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth in,
ſeized of the fee ſimple.</p>
                  <p>Husband and wife Joynt-tenants in tail, make a Leaſe for
life; the husband dies, the fee-ſimple deſcends to his ſon out-living the
wife.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115019:48"/>
                  <head>Who have a ſole eſtate in fee-ſimple, that they may
deviſe it, and who not.</head>
                  <p>A man ſeized of Land in Fee, hath iſſue a daughter
beyond the Seas; and after, he hath another daughter within the Realm, and
dies; the daughters enter together, the younger daughter hath a ſole eſtate
in fee-ſimple.</p>
                  <p>A man is diſſolved by two, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſes all his
right to one of them in tail; he is ſo ſeized in Fee ſimple.</p>
                  <p>One Joynt-tenant releaſeth to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion upon condition:
the Releaſee dieth, his heir enters, the condition is broken, and the
Releaſor enters, clayming the moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the heir ſhall not be ſaid to be
ſole ſeized.</p>
                  <p>Two Coparceners in Fee are impleaded; the one of them
diſclaimeth; the other is not ſole ſeized. The Law is otherwiſe
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Joynttenants.</p>
                  <p>A man ſeizd in fee, hath iſſue two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
baſtards, and one daughter legitimate: the Baſtards, enter; the daughter
legitimate releaſeth to one of them, ſhe is not ſole ſeized.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115019:48"/>
                  <p>Land is given to a man, to have to him together with
<hi>A.</hi> the daughter of the <hi>donor</hi> in frank marriage; after they
are divorced, <hi>cauſa praecontractus,</hi> at the ſuite of the husband;
the <hi>donor</hi> dies, the daughter is his heir; ſhe is ſole
ſeized.</p>
                  <p>A woman inheritrix hath iſſue, a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, her husband
dies; ſhe takes a ſecond husband, and hath iſſue another daughter: the
husband and wife exchange the Land of the wife for other Land in Fee; and after
of the wife and husband die, the daughters enter into the Land taken in
exchange: the younger ſhall be ſaid to be ſole ſeized.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>feme</hi> ſole makes a Feoffment upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to be
performed on the part of the Feoffee at a certain day, before the day they
intermary, the day incurreth, the money not paid: the husband is ſole
ſeized.</p>
                  <p>A Feoffment is made to two, and to their proper uſe; and
livery, &amp; ſeiſin is made to one of them accordingly, he is not ſole
ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: otherwiſe, if no uſe had been expreſſed. A Feoffment is made
by deed to two, with a Letter of Attorney to one of them, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ſeizen,
and he makes livery to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther accordingly: he is not ſole ſeized in
Fee-ſimple.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115019:49"/>
                  <p>Two joynt-Tenants, one within age, are diſeiſed by the
Father of the Infant; and the Father dies ſeized; the Infant enters, and the
other occupieth in Common with him, the Infant is ſole ſeized.</p>
                  <p>Two joynt-Tenants in Fee: the one bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains and fells by
Indenture all his part, and before the Inrolement, the other dies, and the
Indenture is inrolled within the ſix months, the other moyety ſhall
deſcend.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What perſons are Coparceners or Tenants in common in
Fee-ſimple: and who may deviſe their parts, and who not.</head>
                  <p>A man hath two daughters, and makes a leaſe to them for term
of their lives; the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dies; the daughters are ſeized in Fee in
Coparcenary.</p>
                  <p>Land is given to a husband and wife and to a third perſon,
and to the heirs of the husband; and the third perſon releaſeth to the
husband and wife, and to the heirs of the wife: the husband and wife are not
joynt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tenants nor Tenants
in common of the <hi>Fee</hi>-ſimple: but the husband himſelf is ſole
ſeized in Fee.</p>
                  <p>A man hath iſſue, two daughters; and the 
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115019:49"/>elder of them holdeth certain land of the father by 4
<hi>d.</hi> rent, the father dieth, the younger ſiſter ſhal be
preſently ſeized with out any partition of 2 <hi>d.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two joyn-Tenants by deed, make ſuch partition, that is, that
the one of them ſhall have the one moyety to him and his heirs, and the other
ſhall have the other moyety to him and his heirs, without any meets or
bounds, they are not Tenants in common.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a Feofment of two acres of Land <hi>habendum;</hi>
the one acre to one of them and his heirs, and the other acre to the other
&amp; his heirs: they are joynt-tenants.</p>
                  <p>Three Coparceners are agreed to make a partition, ſo that
the one hath a ſeveral part alloted to her in ſeveralty; and that the
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhall hold in Coparcerany: and for equality of partition, a rent is
granted and alotted out of the ſeveral part to the others in Fee: they are
coparcerners of the Rent.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a leaſe for life, and hath iſſue two
daughters, and dieth; the Leſſee make waſte: the one of the daughters
hath iſſue, and dyeth: the iſſue and the other bring a Writ of waſte,
and recover, and enter; they are Coparceners as well of the Free-hold as of the
Fee.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115019:50"/>
                  <p>Land is given to two to have to them, that is to ſay, to the
one of them in tayl, and to the other in Fee: he who hath a Fee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth
the whole, and dieth: this not good for any part.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What deviſes of reverſions or remainders of Rent be
good, and what not.</head>
                  <p>A man lets a leaſe for term of life and after diſeiſed
his Leſſee, and makes a Leaſe for term of life to another: for term of
life of the firſt Leſſee, the remainder over in Fee, the firſt
Leſſee enters, yet he in the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may deviſe his remainder.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a leaſe for yeares upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that the
leſſor diſturb not the Leſſee within the term of the Leaſe, that
the Leſſee ſhal have Fee, &amp; maketh Livery accordingly: the Leſſor
diſturbeth the Leſſee for Rent, where none is in arear, and after he
devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his reverſion: this is not good.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a Leaſe of two acres of Land, reſerving rent,
and hath iſſue two daughters, and dieth, the daughters make partition of
the reverſion; ſo that the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with the appurtenances of one acre
is allotted to one, and the other to the other: <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115019:50"/>they
ſeverally deviſe the rent: this is not good.</p>
                  <p>Land is given to two <hi>habend</hi> to the one for life, and
after his deceaſe to the other in Fee; he who hath the Fee deviſeth his
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: this is good.</p>
                  <p>The husband endows his wife at the Curch-door, and after is
attainted of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and dieth; the wife enters: the Lord of whom the Land is
holden, deviſeth the reverſion, this is not good.</p>
                  <p>A leaſe is made for life: the remainder in Fee to the Wife
of the deviſer, ſhe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viveth, and deviſeth this remainder: this is
good.</p>
                  <p>An Infant makes a Leaſe for life, the Leſſee grants his
eſtate over with Warrants the Infant at his full age bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>geth a <hi>dum fuit infra aetatem,</hi> againſt
the Grantee, who avoucheth his Grantor, who entreth into the warranty, upon
whoſe poſſeſſion the demandant releaſeth in fee al his right, and
is barred in the action by this releaſe, and after deviſeth his
reverſion: this is a good device.</p>
                  <p>A man gran's his reverſion in Fee, and befor attornment he
grants the ſame rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Grantee for term of life onely 
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:115019:51"/>and the Tenant attorneth generally, the Grantee deviſeth
this reverſion: this is a good device.</p>
                  <p>A husband makes a Leaſe for life to the daughter and heir
apparent of his wife, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing covert rendring rent; the wife mother dieth, the
husband deviſeth the rent: this is void.</p>
                  <p>A man makes a leaſe for life, reſerving rent to him and
his heirs, the Leaſſor devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his rent; this is good: but if he
reſerve the Rent to him and to his Aſſigns, it is not good.</p>
                  <p>What gift, or eſtate, or conveyance ſhall be ſaid to be
made by covin or fraud, and what not.</p>
                  <p>A m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n
holdeth Land in Soccage of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lord; and he conveys this by fraud to
defrand the Lord of his relief or herriot, the Lord ſhall not take advantage
of this covin.</p>
                  <p>The Tenant makes an eſtate in Fee upon condition, and takes
back an eſtate to him for liſe, the remainder to his eldeſt ſon in
tail, and for default of ſuch iſſue, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to the heirs of the
Body of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb n="93" facs="tcp:115019:51"/>begotten, the remainder over in Fee to
the Lord of whom the Land is holden, yet this is covin at the pleaſure of the
Lord.</p>
                  <p>A man <hi>bona fide</hi> enfeoffeth two of his ſervants to
their own uſe, for good ſervice done and to be done; and they by covin
convey divers faandulent eſtates to their maſters, which remains over,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the maſter knowing of their intent rejoyneth at it, yet
this ſhall not be fraud.</p>
                  <p>The Tenant intending fraud, enfeoffeth divers perſons, and
putteth the Lord in truſt as Attorney, to make Livery and Seizin, and ſo he
doth, yet the Lord ſhall avoid this covin.</p>
                  <p>The Tenant maketh a Leaſe for years to the Lord, and after
by a Fine conveyeth fraudulent Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and after, the Lord
within the term, maketh his Executor, and dieth, and the Execu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or entreth into the term, and
after the leſſor dieth, his Heir within age, and the term continueth, the
Heir of the Lord ſhall not avoid this covin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115019:52"/>
                  <head>What ſhall be ſaid a purchaſe of Lands by the husband
for the Joynture of the wife, and what not.</head>
                  <p>Land is given to three men, and a <hi>feme</hi> ſole: one of
them marries with the <hi>feme;</hi> ſhe being excommunicated, one of the
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers releaſeth to the husbandand wife, and to the Heirs of the husband:
the husband dies, the wife aſſents. This is a good Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, and yet the
wife is not a Tenant for life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> being contracted; marri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h another wife, and after marrieth her with whom
he was contracted: he and his wife exchange land, which he had in the right of
his wife: the husband dieth; ſhe agreeth to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change; this is not a
joynture.</p>
                  <p>A windmil is leaſed to a woman for years, who taketh a
husband, he granteth the term upon condition, and for the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion broken
enters: the leſſor releaſeth them, <hi>&amp; haeredibus ſuis omnibus
maſculis:</hi> and if they die without ſuch an Heir, that this ſhall
remain to the Heirs of the husband: this is good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 27. H. 8.
cap. 10.</p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115019:52"/>
                  <p>A Reverſion upon an eſtate for years is deviſed to the
husband and wife in free marriage by the father of the husband, the remainder
to <hi>J. S.</hi> in fee Tenant for yeers ſurrendeth to the husband, who
dieth; the wife enters: this a good eſtate to the wife; <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An upper chamber is granted without deed to <hi>A.</hi> for
life, the remainder for life; the remainder to <hi>A</hi> in Fee: <hi>A.</hi>
grants his eſtate to him in remainder and his wife, and to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Heirs; and if they die without
Heirs males of their bodies begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that then this ſhall revert: the
husband dies, the wife enters. This is an eſtate to the wife,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Land is deviſed to <hi>J. S.</hi> for life, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder
to a husband in frank-marriage for, <hi>&amp;c. I. S.</hi> and the deviſer
die; the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band enters and dies, the wife euters: this is not an eſtate
made, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Five acres of Land, adjoyning to the Sea are deviſed to
husband and wife, <hi>&amp; haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus ſuis maſculis,</hi> for,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> five other acres adjoyning thereunto, the Sea for ſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
into which the husband and wife en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: this is not any eſtate made in the
five acres newly gained.</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:115019:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>J. S.</hi> by indenture bargains and ſells a Dove
houſe to husband and wife, and to their heirs ſo long as they have
iſſue of their bodies, whereas he hath no Dove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe: <hi>J. S.</hi>
builded one; the husband enters and Dies, the wife enters: this is no tail in
Joynture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The father giveth Land to the ſon and his wife, <hi>&amp;

liberis ſuis,</hi> with warranty to the ſon and his Wife, and to the heirs
of their bodies for ten years; they are impleaded within the ten years, and
loſe and have in value: the years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, the husband dies, the wife enters:
this is not an eſtate in tail for joynture, but for life.</p>
                  <p>Land is given to <hi>A</hi> and <hi>B</hi> and to the heirs of
<hi>B. B.</hi> leaſeth this to a <hi>feme</hi> ſole for life, the
leſſor grants to the ſaid <hi>feme,</hi> and <hi>J. D.</hi> common for
ten year out of the ſaid Land, during their lives for the Joynture of
leſſee, and after marrieth her: <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>D.</hi> die: this is an
eſtate conveyed for life as an hereditament.</p>
                  <p>To grant an annuity of 10 <hi>l.</hi> joyntly and ſeverally,
to <hi>J. S.</hi> in Fee, who granteth it to husband and wife, to the husband
for the life of <hi>J. D.</hi> to the wife until one of <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115019:53"/>the
ſons of <hi>J. S.</hi> accompliſh the age of twenty one yeers, the husband
dieth, the wife accepteth this annuity this is an eſtate made for the wife
for a joynture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Leaſe for life is made to the husband, the remainder to
his wife and <hi>J. D.</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive for their lives; the husband
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elleth trees and dies, the
wife enters, the Vendee cuts, the leſſor recovers in a Writ of waſt, and
hath execution: this is an eviction by lawful action: and yet the wife ſhall
not have a Writ of Dower.</p>
                  <p>A Lordſhip by fealty and rent, is give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to Baron and <hi>fem:</hi> in tall before
marrige, for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the remainder in ſee a Tenancy eſcheateth
the husband, leaſeth the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>A.</hi> who recovereth in a <hi>Ceſſavit,</hi>
and dies, his heir entert, the husband dies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this is an eviction by lawful
action, and the wife ſhall recover but an eſtate for life to the value of
the Tenancy.</p>
                  <p>Tenant in tail of a rent, purchaſeth the Land, out of which,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> in tall, and giveth into Baron and <hi>feme</hi> for their
lives, for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fifty yeers expire, Tenant in tail, and the
husband die, the wife enters, theiſſue bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Formedon of the rent
&amp; recovereth, and is put in execution: this is an eviction, 
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115019:54"/>and the wife ſhall have it to the value of the rent.</p>
                  <p>Land is granted to a <hi>feme</hi> covert for life, for,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> he in reverſion grants it by Fyne: the Conuſee brings a
<hi>ſcire facias,</hi> the husband claims Fee, and it is found againſt him,
whereby judgement is given, the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band dies, the wife enters, the recoverer
enters: this is not an eviction.</p>
                  <p>Tenant after poſſibility of iſſue extinct, the
remainder for life is diſciſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed to the diſeiſor, who
dies: his heir gives the Land to husband and wife in tail, Tenant for life
bringeth <hi>a conſimili caſu,</hi> and recovers; the wife enters; this is
not an eviction.</p>
                  <p>An Infant gives a Park to a <hi>feme</hi> covert for life
without impeachment of waſte, the remainders of them to two men, and the
heirs of their bodies: the game is deſtroyed, the husband dies, the wife
enters, they bring a Wrie of waſte, the wife pleadeth <hi>Nul</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereby they
recover: this is a lawful eviction, but ſhe ſhall not have a Writ of
error.</p>
                  <p>Land of the value of 20 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> is granted to a
<hi>feme</hi> for life, rendring 10 <hi>l. per annum;</hi> ſhe marrieth: he
who hath <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115019:54"/>right recovereth the Land by covin of the husband,
and hath Execution; the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being Tenant in Tail, dies, having Land to
the value of 10 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> the wife ſhall have it diſcharged of
the rent, leſſe for life reverſing rent, the leſſor diſeiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
him and makes a feoſment, the feoffee dies, his heir giveth the land to the
leſſor and his wife in tail for her joynture. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for life brings a
writ of entry in the poſt, and recovereth, and hath execution, the husband
dies, the wife ſhal have dower, and ſhall recover for life the rent not
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in value.</p>
                  <p>Grandfather, father and ſon, the father diſeiſeth the
grandfather, and taketh a wife; the father ſurrendreth certain Copy-hold land
to the uſe of himſelf and his wife, and the heirs of the husband: the
father dies, the ſon enters, the grandfather dies, the wife ſhall have this
joynture or dowr, but not of this land.</p>
                  <p>Land is given to husband and wife in tail, with warranty, they
loſe and recover in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue againſt him who hath nothing: the husband and
<hi>J. S.</hi> being joynt-Tenants, agree by deed, that after five yeers ended,
they ſhall hold in ſeveralty; the husband <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115019:55"/>dies within
the five yeers, the wife hath dower aſſigned, ſhe ſhall have both.</p>
                  <p>Lord and Tenant: the Tenant is attaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Felony, and
commiteth Treaſon, for which he is attainted the Lord enters, and gives the
land to the Tenant and his wife for yeers, upon condition, that if the Lord do
not pay 20 <hi>l.</hi> to the husband and wife at a certain day, that they
ſhall have it in tail, for the wives joynture: and the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, dies
before the day, the money is not paid: this is a joynture, and the wife ſhall
not have dower.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> enfeoffeth <hi>J. R.</hi> and <hi>B.</hi> makes
livery to <hi>J. S.</hi> who taketh a wife; land is given to them in ſpecial
tail for the joynture of the wiſe, they levy a fine. <hi>J. S.</hi> dies, a
<hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe</hi> is brought againſt <hi>B.</hi> he diſclaims; the heir of
<hi>J. S.</hi> enters, the wife ſhall not have joynture nor dower of the
land, but of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther land ſhe ſhall have dower.</p>
                  <p>A rent-charge iſſuing out of Lands in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Counties,
and in the hands of ſeveral perſons, is granted to husband for life, the
remainder to his wife for her life for her joynture; the husband dies, the
Tenant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torns to the wife, ſhe ſhall not have this joynture not
dower.</p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:115019:55"/>
                  <p>Land is given to <hi>J. S.</hi> for life, the leſſor
diſeiſeth him, and giveth the land before Coverture to the wife for life
for a joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a ſtranger confirmeth her eſtate with warranty; <hi>I.
S.</hi> bringeth a <hi>Praecipe</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covereth, the wife hath in value,
the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and he in reverſion make a feofment before the Statute, the
husband dies: this is not an eviction by diſcontinuance of the joynture, and
yet ſhe ſhall recover dower.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What is a ioynture aſſured before marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and what a
joynture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter marriage.</head>
                  <p>A Lordſhip by fealty and Rent before marriage is granted to
Baron and <hi>feme</hi> for a joynture, they marry; a Tenancy eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth,
the husband enters and dies; this is a joynture in the Tenancy aſſured
before marriage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>J. S.</hi> contracts with <hi>A.</hi> and before
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, concludes with <hi>B.</hi> that he will reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Mannor of
<hi>D.</hi> and that this ſhall be to them in tail for a Joynture.
<hi>B.</hi> brings a writ of entry, which is returned, they marry. <hi>B.</hi>
recovers and enters: this is a joynture after marriage.</p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115019:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> leaſeth to two for yeers rendring rent, and
grants the reverſion to husband and wife for their lives for a joynture, one
attorneth before marriage, and the other after marriage: this is a good
joynture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore marriage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> enfeoffeth <hi>I. D.</hi> to the uſe of
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf until he marry, and after that he marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, then to the uſe of
her that ſhall be his wife for her for a joynture: this is a joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture after
marriage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> grants land to a <hi>feme</hi> for ten years,
and if he after marry her, then ſhe ſhall have it for her life for a
joynture, they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; this is a joynture before marriage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> in conſideration of a marriage to be had
betwixt him and <hi>A. S.</hi> covenanteth that he ſhall be ſeiſed to the
uſe of him and the ſaid <hi>A.</hi> for their lives; they intermarry, the
deed is inrolled, this is a joynture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore marriage.</p>
                  <p>After affiance between <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>A. S.</hi> they
conclude that a fyne ſhall be leavied of the Mannor of <hi>D,</hi> for her
joynture, the concord is acknowledged before the chief Juſtice; they marry,
and after a writ of Covenant is brought, and a fyne leavied: this is a joynture
after marriage.</p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:115019:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> and <hi>A.</hi> marry before yeers of
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, land is given to them for their lives, at the yeers of conſent
they agree: this is a joynture after marriage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> makes a deed of feoffment to <hi>A.</hi> with a
letter of Attorney, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eofment <hi>A.</hi> doth expreſs to be to the uſe of himſelf,
and her who ſhal be his wife for their lives, for a joynture; they marry, the
Attorney maketh livery: this is a joynture after mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I. S.</hi> diſeiſeth one to the uſe of <hi>A.</hi>
and <hi>B.</hi> whom he intends ſhall marry for a joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>A.</hi> and
<hi>B.</hi> enter, and after the diſeiſe releaſeth to the wife for her
joynture: this is a joynture after marriage.</p>
                  <p>Land is given to <hi>A, B.</hi> and her who ſhall be his
wife, for a joynture; they marry, the wife enters; this is a joynture in the
moye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which ſhe ſhall have by ſurvivor, and before marriage.</p>
                  <p>A deviſeth, that his Executor ſhall give the Mannor of
<hi>D.</hi> to <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>A. D.</hi> who ſhall be his wife, for
their lives; they inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marry, the Executor grants the Mannor accordingly; This
is a joynture before marriage.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:115019:57"/>
               <head>Some Caſes reſolved touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forceable Entries, by the
Statute of 8 <hi>H.</hi> 6. c. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The turbulency of ſome troubleſome Spirits, oftentimes
cauſe great miſchief in this caſe, who have the Law in their own hands,
and altogether be their own carvers in laying hold on violently whatſoever
they imagine their own, not regarding the mark or touchſtone whereby it
ſhould be proved: from whence ariſe tumults, affrays, riots, aſſaults,
mayhems, man ſlaughters and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſelf: for preventien of which evil,
the Statute of</hi> 8 H. 6. <hi>hath provided remedies, and given power to the
Juſtices of Peace to ſuppreſs ſuch mi demeanors; and becauſe the
Country people are much infeſted with this maligne diſeaſe, for whoſe
instruction this Treatiſe is chiefly intended, I ſhall here give them
ſome 'Directions in this Caſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:115019:57"/>
                  <head>What is a forceable entry, and what is a forceable
detaining, and what not.</head>
                  <p>If two perſons or more being armed, or having weapons in
their hands, enter the houſe of another to have poſſeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
and thereupon the party in the houſe parts a far off without any further
violence offered him, this is a forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>If two men or more armed <hi>&amp;c</hi> enter the houſe of
another, the door being open, not declaring their intent, and remain in quiet
notwithſtanding, the Tenants without u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing violence: this is not a
forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>But if two or more enter the houſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in peaceable
manner, and after with fore and violence againſt the will of the party in
poſſeſſion put him out of poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: this is a forceable
entry.</p>
                  <p>If a ſingle perſon break the houſe or window of another
and enter in, againſt his will, and thereupon he threatens the party in
poſſeſſion, inſomuch that for fear he forſakes the houſe: this is
a forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>If a forceable entry be made into the <pb n="106" facs="tcp:115019:58"/>houſe of another to fight with the party there dwelling; and he for
fear departs out of the houſe, and his enemies alſo; this is not a
forceable entry:</p>
                  <p>If a man make a leaſe for life, and after grant the
reverſion to the ſame leſſee upon condition, which is broken on the
part of the leſſee, and thereupon the leſſor enters with force to gain
the poſſeſſion of the land: this is a forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>But if the leſſor enter with force to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> if waſte be made by the
leſſee; this is not a forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>A Lord diſtrain for rent with force, though none be arear:
this is not a forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>If any be fighting in a houſe, &amp; the door ſhut, and
others enter, and break it to ſee the peace kept: this not a forceable
entry.</p>
                  <p>If two perſons are fighting in the ſtreet, and one wound
the other, ſo that he is in danger of death, and flee into a houſe, and
ſhut the doors after him, and others there preſent purſue him, and break
the houſe to take him: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is is not a forceable entry.</p>
                  <p>But if no ſuch danger of his life be, then they cannot break
the houſe to take him, although it be done upon freſh ſuite; but if the
door be open, they may enter and take him.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:115019:58"/>
                  <p>If the Juſtices of peace upon complaint made come to the
place where the force was, and find the door ſhut, and within the houſe
there is but one ſole perſon, who will not open the door, &amp; ſuffer
the Juſtices to come in: this is a detaining with force.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices come to the place where the force was, and
find ſome perſons in arms, or their weapons lying by them in the houſe;
this is a detainder with force.</p>
                  <p>If a man hath two houſes neer adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the one by a good
title, the other by a defeazible title; he keeps a force in the firſt houſe
to beat them who would enter into the houſe by a defeazible title; this is a
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of force within.</p>
                  <p>If a man claim common in any Land, and the Land is detained
with force, when he would uſe his common, or diſtrain for his Rent: this is
a detaining with force.</p>
                  <p>If a man hear that certain fellows will come to his houſe to
kill, beat or rob him: whereupon he aſſembles a force to aſſiſt him
in his defence, this is no detaining with force.</p>
                  <p>If a man hath rent iſſuing out of the land of another,
which land is detained with force, when he would diſtrain for his rent 
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:115019:59"/>arear, he who is ſo diſturbed of this rent, is no
party grieved to complain by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute before recited.</p>
                  <p>If after the death of the father, a ſtranger enters by
abatement into the land, and holdeth with force, the ſon is not a party
grieved.</p>
                  <p>If a man be ſeized of land, upon which a forceable entry is
made, and die before any complaint is made thereof, his heir is not a party
grieved to make complaint.</p>
                  <p>If a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
make a leaſe for five yeers upon condition that if within the firſt two
yeers, the leſſee pay to him 10 <hi>l.</hi> that then he ſhall have fee,
and livery is made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly there, if any ſuch forceable entry be
committed within five yeers, although that the condition be not performed, yet
th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leſſee is a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rty grieved by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>A man poſſeſſed of a term makes the heirs of <hi>J.
S.</hi> his Executors, and dies; the ſaid <hi>J. S.</hi> being alſo then
dead, leaving iſſue a daughter, his wife <hi>pregnant</hi> with another
daughter; the firſt enters into the land after which the other is born, and
then ſuch a force is committed; both the daughters are parties grieved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:115019:59"/>
                  <head>Who are bound to ge with the Juſtices at their command to
remove a force; what is their penalty in caſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to go; and of
what force is the Iuſtices record.</head>
                  <p>A man attainted of Felony upon requeſt made is bound to go
with the Juſtices to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move a force.</p>
                  <p>Dukes, Earls, Lords, Barons, and every Apprentice and Servant
is bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> by the Statute to go
with the Juſtices to remove a force.</p>
                  <p>An Alien born, and not made a Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, or a man who is not of
ſound memory, an Infant within the age of fourteen yeers, or any woman ſole
or covert, are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellable to go with the Juſtices to remove a
force.</p>
                  <p>A man going under bayl for debt or treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, is not bound
to go.</p>
                  <p>If hue and cry be made at one end of the Town, and the
Juſtices require them at the other end of the Town, they are bound to go with
the Juſtice to remove a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce.</p>
                  <p>But if they have taken a Fellon, or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are in purſuit of a
Fellon at the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, <pb n="110" facs="tcp:115019:60"/>they are not bound to
go:</p>
                  <p>If the Sheriff, Conſtable or other Officer without any
Warrant, Proceſs or Precept, require any perſon to go with the Juſtices
to remove a force: they are not bound to go by this Statute; neither can an
Officer arreſt or impriſon them by this Statute for their refuſal.</p>
                  <p>But the Juſtices themſelves may require them being in
their preſence by word only, and upon their refuſal, impriſon and fyne
them.</p>
                  <p>If a forceable entry, and detainer with force be made upon the
poſſeſſion of a Juſtice of peace, he himſelf upon the view of it
cannot remove the force.</p>
                  <p>But if upon a force committed, they alſo aſſault the
Juſtice himſelf, then he may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to priſon.</p>
                  <p>If one part of a houſe be in one County, and another part in
another County; and when the Juſtices come to remove the force before they
can arreſt them, they go into another part of the houſe which is in
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther County; there they cannot remove the force by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>If a man enter the houſe of another by force, and expels the
owner thereof, to one <pb n="111" facs="tcp:115019:60"/>part or end of the ſaid houſe,
and detain the houſe with force; the Juſtices may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move this force, and
commit the offendor to priſon.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices be preſent upon other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, where
a forceable entry is made, when they are informed thereof, before any
detainder, they cannot arreſt them, and commit them to priſon by this
Statute.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices come to remove a force; and upon an arreſt
made, the offendors eſcape into another County, the Juſtices cannot
arreaſt them nor commit them to priſon by this Statute, although it be upon
freſh ſuite.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices come to remove a force, and the offendors,
before any arreſt, make an eſcape for that time, but in the morning they
are brought back again before the ſame Juſtices to the ſame place, by
vertue of their Precept, yet they cannot commit them by vertue of this
Statute.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtice come to remove a force, and before that they
can arreſt the offenders they eſcape from thence; upon that, the Juſtices
may well record this detainer with force by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>If the Sheriff is made Juſtice of peace, 
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:115019:61"/>and after in the ſame yeer that he is Sheriff he cometh
to the place where the force was, he cannot make a Record of this by the
Statute.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices upon their coming to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the force, make
a Record thereof, and commit the offendors to priſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and although it
appeareth by the ſame Record, That it was not a force upon the matter, yet no
remedy for the party ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices make a Record, That they did ſee, where
indeed there is no ſuch matter, yet the parties cannot traverſe it.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices come to remove a force, and a Reſcue is
made to the Officers and others there preſent to remove them, they may Record
that as well as the force.</p>
                  <p>But if the Juſtices upon view of a force, record a Murder,
Maim, or Man slaughter, this is no Record by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices upon a force committed and complaint thereof
made, make enquiry thereof, without going to the place it ſelf where the
force was: this is alſo a good enquiry by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>But if the Juſtices upon view of the force, 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:115019:61"/>make a Record thereof, and their Record containeth that
the force was made with twenty perſons, and the inquiry found it but ten
perſons: this enquiry is not good by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>If ſeveral enquiries be made by ſeveral Juſtices, upon a
forceable entry, every one of them is a good enquiry.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices in their inquiry of force, preſent an
Inqueſt by perſons not ſworn to do it; the inquiry maketh mention that
they were ſworn, yet this is a good enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                  <p>But if the enquiry be made under the number of twelve: this is
not a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</p>
                  <p>If any of the jurors, before whom any ſuch Inqueſt is
taken, be attained of a falſe Oath, or in <hi>decies tantum,</hi> or are
<hi>Ambo-dexters:</hi> this is not a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</p>
                  <p>But if there be twelve perſons in the jury over and above
the perſons attainted, the inqueſt is good.</p>
                  <p>If it be found by inqueſt that <hi>A. B.</hi> was ſeized,
until <hi>J. D.</hi> diſeiſed him with force by this inquiry, <hi>A.
B.</hi> ſhall have reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:115019:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:115019:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:115019:63"/>
                  <p>If it be found that the father made a leaſe for years, and
died, the years expired; and before any entry made by the ſon, a force is
committed; the ſon ſhall not have reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>A man ſeized of Land hath iſſue a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and dieth,
his wife great with child of a ſon, the daughter is ouſted by force, and
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Son is born, and all this matter is found by inqueſt; yet the Son
ſhall not have reſtitution but the daughter ſhall have it:</p>
                  <p>If it be found by ſeveral Inqueſts, that a man is ouſted
with force by ſeveral perſons at ſundry times of one and the ſame
thing; each Inqueſt is good, and he may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution upon which of
them he will; but when he hath reſtitution upon the one, then he ſhall not
have reſtitution upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>If it be found by ſeveral inquiries (that is to ſay) by
one inqueſt, That <hi>J. S.</hi> is ouſted by force; and by another
Inqueſt, That <hi>J. D:</hi> is ouſted with force, and all of one and the
ſame Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ach
of them may have reſtitution by theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries.</p>
                  <p>If it be found that two joynt-Tenants were ouſted by force,
the one may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution <pb n="115" facs="tcp:115019:63"/>upon this enquiry without
his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion.</p>
                  <p>If it be found that <hi>A. B.</hi> was ſeiſed for the Term
of <hi>D.</hi> and he is ouſted with force by <hi>E.</hi> and that
<hi>D.</hi> is now dead, yet <hi>A. B.</hi> ſhall have reſtitution by this
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry.</p>
                  <p>If it be found that the Father was ſeized until ouſted
with force, and died before any reſtitution or entry, the ſon ſhall not
have any reſtitution.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe if a man be poſſeſſed of a leaſe for
years, and is ouſted thereof with force, and dieth before reſtitution, his
Executors ſhall not have reſtitution by this enquiry.</p>
                  <p>A leſſee for life, the remainder over in fee, the
leſſee is ouſted with force, and all this matter found by inquiſition
of the force but he in the remainder ſhall not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution by this
enquiry.</p>
                  <p>The husband and wife before iſſue had, are ouſted with
force, and then have iſſue, the wife dieth, the husband by inquiry ſhall
have reſtitution.</p>
                  <p>If a Leſſe for life be ouſted with force, and the
leſſor entereth for condition brok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and this is found by Inqueſt, yet
the leſſee ſhal have reſtitution by this enquiry.</p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:115019:64"/>
                  <p>The Juſtices of Peace before inquiry be taken, may put the
party in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on again without any Writ; but noe other Juſtices
can do it without Writ.</p>
                  <p>The Juſtices of the ſame County, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord being before
them, may award ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption by Writ, although they be not the ſame Juſtices
before whom the inqueſt was taken; but not without the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</p>
                  <p>If the Juſtices who took the inqueſt be dead before
reſtitution be made, yet the Juſtices having the record may award
exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ſame: the Judges of the Upper-Bench having the Record
removed before them, may award Execution by this Statute by Writ; but not
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife.</p>
                  <p>If a Tenant of Land payes any rent to a ſtranger by
compulſion of diſtreſs taken with force: this is a diſſeiſin with
force.</p>
                  <p>But if a man be diſſeiſſed of any rent by the Tenant
of the Land, or by <hi>Reſcous</hi> with force<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: this is not a deſſeiſin with force.</p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115019:64"/>
                  <p>If the Lord improves the waſte with force, not leaving
ſufficient Common for the Commoners: this is a diſſeiſin with force
within the compaſs of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
                  <p>If a leſſee for years with the remainder over for life be
ouſted with force: this is not a diſſeſin with force by the
Statute.</p>
                  <p>If the diſſeiſor, after he hath continued in quiet
poſſeſſion for three years, detaineth with force; this is not any
detaining with force by the Statute.</p>
                  <p>If two joynt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tenants are diſſeiſed with force,
they both together are the parties grieved by this Statute, and not apart; but
if one of them releaſeth to the other, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, then the other by himſelf
is a party grieved.</p>
                  <p>If the husband and wife ſeiſed of Lands in right of the
wife, are diſſeiſed with force and the husband dieth, the wife ſhall be
a party grieved by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>If a man be ſeiſed in right of his wife, and
diſſeiſſed with force, and after they have iſſue, the wife dieth,
the husband is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>party grieved by this Statute.</p>
                  <p>If a man makes a leaſe for life to his eldeſt ſon, and
is diſſeiſſed with force, and <pb n="118" facs="tcp:115019:65"/>dieth, the Son is
the party grieved.</p>
                  <p>Land deſcends to two daughters, one enters, and a ſtranger
ouſted her by force, ſhe may have an aſſize by this Statute: the party
grieved may have an aſſize of <hi>novel diſſeiſin,</hi> or an action
of treſpaſs upon the Statute, reciting the Statute, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
treble damages.</p>
                  <p>Alſo in a Writ of Attainder brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Jurors,
if they finde for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant by falſe Oath, the party ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
treble damages.</p>
                  <p>And theſe offences, I hope all Friends to peace and truth
will avoid, and hereby finde directions to puniſh the <hi>nocent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:115019:65"/>
               <head>An Abſtract of ſeveral penal Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes made and enacted
for the good of the Subjects, but are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day ſhamefully broken: therefore
I have, according to promiſe inſerted the ſeveral pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties by them
enjoyned accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of the offence, to terrifie Offendors for
fear of the puniſhment, <hi>(though they have ſo many partakers, that it
will not reſtrain them)</hi> and to excite others effectually to proſecute
them for the love of <hi>Virtue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WE will not here</hi> actum agere, <hi>not uſe ſo
much</hi> Tautology, <hi>as to inſert what we have already ſpoken of; but
onely put you in mind, That we have before in the Charge of the</hi>
Court-Leet, <hi>ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſected the Alehouſes, perhaps more
then my Hoſtes will thank me <pb n="120" facs="tcp:115019:66"/>for; and given a hint at
the Gaming-Houſes too, becauſe the Alehouſes and they are inſeparable
Inmates; yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, they are not ſo fully laid down as I finde the
Statute mentions: wherefore therewith I'll first begin.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Gaming-houſes, and Players at Games.</head>
                  <p>No perſon whatſoever ſhall keep, hold, ſuffer or
maintain in his Houſe, Yard, Orchard or Backſide, any place of unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
Games; nor ſhall not permit nor ſuffer any perſons to play at his
Houſe, Yard Backſide or Orchard, at Tables, Cards, Dice Coits, Loggats,
Claſh, Bowls, Slide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriſt or Shovegroat, (called now Shuffle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board and
Boards end) or at any other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Game, invented or to be invented, on pain
to forfeit for every day he ſhall uſe or ſuffer the ſame, 40
<hi>s.</hi> and all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as ſhall uſe or haunt any ſuch
place of unlawful Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, or
pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y thereat, forfeits 6
<hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> for every ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
                  <p>No Artificer or his Journey-man, no Husband-man, Apprentice,
Labourer, <pb n="121" facs="tcp:115019:66"/>Servant at Husbandry; Marrriner, Fiſher-man,
Water-man or Serving-man, ſhall play at any ſuch unlawful Game or Games out
of <hi>Chriſt-mas;</hi> nor then, out of their Maſter's Houſe, or
preſence; on pain of 20 <hi>s.</hi> for every default 20 <hi>s.</hi> All
which forſeitures are to be divided between the King and any perſon that
will ſue for the ſame in any Court of Record; laying his Action in the
ſame County where the Offence is committed, and proſecuting the ſame
within a year, 33 <hi>H.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>If Informers would look diligently after theſe offences,
they would do good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Commonwealth, and ſave many Families,
Wives and Children from Deſtruction, and Gameſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s from the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, where they uſually throw
their laſt Caſt.</p>
                  <p>All Licenſes to keep Houſes or places of unlawful Games,
ſhall be void, <hi>Stat.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>p. m.</hi> 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:115019:67"/>
                  <head>Perjury.</head>
                  <p>Whoſoever ſuborns a Witneſs to give falſe Teſtimony
in any Court of Record, forfeits 40 <hi>l.</hi> and upon conviction, if he hath
not wherewith to ſatisfie the penalty, he ſhall ſuffer ſix mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hs impriſonment, ſtand in the Pillory an
hour, and be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled for a Witneſs for ever after, unleſſe the
judgment given againſt him be reverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by attaint or error.</p>
                  <p>And he that doth wilfully <hi>forſwear</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that
is, commit <hi>wilſull perjury,</hi> ſhall forfeit 20 <hi>b.</hi> ſix
months impriſonment, and be diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abled for a Witneſs, unleſs the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be
reverſed; and if he cannot pay the Fine, he is to ſtand in the Pillory, and
have both his ears nailed, <hi>Stat.</hi> 5. <hi>El.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>forſwearing,</hi> I mean giving falſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
upon Oath before a judge of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; and this is <hi>Perjury:</hi> for if a man
bring an Action on the Caſe for ſcandalous words againſt another, for
ſaying of the Plaintiff he forſwore himſelf; it wil not bear an Action,
unleſs he ſay he forſwore him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <pb n="123" facs="tcp:115019:67"/>in a Court,
which is a Court of Record being called there for a Witneſs.</p>
                  <p>And here by the way <hi>I</hi> muſt needs mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a Caſe
which is odious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>T. S.</hi> of <hi>W.</hi> ſubborns <hi>H. S.</hi> his
Son to give falſe evidence in the Court of Record holden for the Honor and
Caſtle of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> in a Cauſe there depending between <hi>F. W.
&amp;c.</hi> he had done the ſame before at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> and hath
ſince therewith <hi>W. F.</hi> againſt the ſame <hi>F<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> W.</hi> upon
an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>H. S.</hi> commits wilful Perjury at <hi>Windſor,</hi> is
found thereof guilty by Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>W.</hi> (where there was no
Seſſions kept a long time before) nor (becauſe of their kind uſage to
the Country, ſince) at the Seiſſions: the buſineſs was ſo handled
by <hi>Tom Sneaks,</hi> and his Friends, that it was alledged that
<hi>Windſor.</hi> Court was not a Court of Record, and unleſs the
Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor preſently prove it, (which they knew upon an inſtant he could
not) the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſhould be acquitted; and ſo he was thereupon.
<hi>Rare</hi> Juſtice! But in the Court of <hi>W.</hi> it is no wonder.</p>
                  <p>I could name two or three more admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Preſidents between
theſe parties: and <pb n="124" facs="tcp:115019:68"/>ſome acted in the Town-Court of
<hi>Oking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, inter Sims</hi> and <hi>Magick;</hi> but I'll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them
till another time for another intended Subject.</p>
                  <p>The Forfeitures in Caſe of <hi>Perjury</hi> are to be
recovered in any Court of Record by Action of Debt or Information, one half to
the King, the other to the Proſecutor; and may be laid in any County, though
the Offence was not committed there.</p>
                  <p>This Act ought to be proclaimed at every Aſſize; and great
pitty it is in my opinion, that there is no greater puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ordained for
<hi>Perjury.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is in al reſpects equivalent to murder; and why ſhould
not the committers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, receive the ſame puniſhment as mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers
convicted do? or at leaſt ſhould do.</p>
                  <p>He that will forſwear himſelf, as too many now a days make
no bones of it, oftentimes doth, and upon any ſpleen, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or revenge,
will take away the eſtate and life of any one.</p>
                  <p>Did not <hi>T. S.</hi> at <hi>Oke-ingham</hi> ſwear
a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>F. W.</hi> at <hi>Abingdon,</hi> that he had ſtollen ſix
cocks of Hay from him worth ſix ſhillings, and brough his Son and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115019:68"/>to do the ſame? when there was not a Hay-cock in the
Ground: but the ſaid <hi>F. W.</hi> was deputed lawfully to gather Tythes
which the other very wel knew, and did take but two or three little Graſs
cocks valued at three pence, which was his right: yet the other endeavoured to
hang him for it, if his <hi>Perjury</hi> had not appeared too manifeſtly, as
well as it hath done ſince; as I ſhall ſhortly in another intended
Subject fully demonſtrate and anatomize the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the Court of
<hi>Oke-ing ham</hi> beſides. But I'll forbear them now, becauſe the
ſcope of this is ſomething elſe, to which I'll pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Foreſtallers, Regradors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſers,</head>
                  <p>If any Perſon ſhall buy or contract for any Merchandize,
Victuals, or any other thing whatſoever, in the way, by Land or Water, before
it be brought unto any City, Fair or Market where it ought to be ſold; or
ſhall cauſe the ſame to be ſo brought; or ſhall diſſwade the
people from bringing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch commodity to any ſuch place; or, being
brought, ſhall perſwade them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance <pb n="126" facs="tcp:115019:69"/>the price
thereof, ſhall be adjudged a foreſtaller, <hi>Stat.</hi> 5. <hi>Ed.</hi>
6.14.</p>
                  <p>A Regrador is he that buys any Grain, Wine, Fiſh, Butter,
Cheeſe, Candles, Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Sheep, Lambs, Calves, Swine, Pigs, Geeſe, Capons,
Hens, Chickens, Pidgeons, Conies or other dead Victual whatſoever, brought to
a Fair or Market to be ſold there, and to ſel the ſame again in the
ſame Fair or Market, or in ſome other Fair or Market within four miles.</p>
                  <p>An Ingroſſer is he that gets into his hands by buying,
contract or promiſe, (other then by device or Grant) any Corn grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the
Fields, or other Grain, Butter, Cheeſe, Fiſh, or other dead Victuals
what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever with intent to ſell it again. The Offend or in any of theſe
Caſes, ſhall forfeit for the firſt offence, the value of the goods ſo
bought, and two months impriſonment without Bayl: for the ſecond offence,
the double value, and ſix months impriſonment without Bayl: and for the
third ſhall forfeit all his goods, be ſet on the Pillory, and be
impriſoned at the Kings pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>He that buyeth Grain in any Market for change of Seed, ſhall
bring as much hither the ſame day and ſell it, according to the 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:115019:69"/>preſent price of Grain, on pain to forfeit double the
value of the Grain ſo bought.</p>
                  <p>He that buyes any Cattel, and ſells the ſame alive within
five weeks, ſhall forfeit the double value therof, during which time he ought
to keep them upon Paſture, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had by grant or preſcripition. Theſe
Offences ſhal be divided between the King and the proſecutor.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Wine without Licenſe.</head>
                  <p>No perſon whatſoever not lawfully au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by
Licenſe, ſhall ſell or utter any Wine by retail to be ſpent in his or
their manſion-houſe, or in any other place, in their tenure by any colour,
craft, or engine, on pain of 10 <hi>l.</hi> to be divided between the King and
the Proſecutor: which ſuit ſhall be comenced within a year after the
offence committed, <hi>Stat</hi> 7. <hi>E.</hi> 6.5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>Underſtand, no colour, craft nor engine ſhall evade the
penalty of this Statute: it is not the pretence of the keeping a free Vintner,
as they call it, nor taking their Wine of a Vintner, or other ſuch pretences
may ſerve their turn.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:115019:70"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of importing Silk or Ribbands,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>None ſhall bring or cauſe to be brought into
<hi>England</hi> any Silk wrought (by it ſelf or other ſtuff) out of
<hi>England</hi> in Riband, Laces, Girdles, Corſes, Cawls, Tiſſues, or
points, on pain to forfeit the lameor the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue thereof: to be divided between
the King and any one that ſhall ſeize or ſue for the ſame,
<hi>Stat.</hi> 19. <hi>H.</hi> 7.21.</p>
                  <p>A general complaint is now made by moſt, nay all Tradeſmen
that work in Silk of the great damage to the Engliſh <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture</hi> in
Silk, by reaſon of the Ribands and wrought Silk brough into this Nation by
the French and Dutch and thoſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Nations, to the great hindrance and
decay of our Engliſh Trade: for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, I have the rather
quoted this Statute to diſcover a remedy for my grieved Country-men in this
behalf, by which they may wright themſelves if they look after it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:115019:70"/>
                  <head>Wood.</head>
                  <p>There are ſuch waſtes and devaſtations of Wood and
Timber, and the growth thereof, in this Nation, as predicates a ſad event and
inevitable calamity enſuing, if it be not timely prevented, (though I am half
afraid, it is too late already, but hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) and do hereby invite all
lovers of their countries good, effectually to put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice all ſuch Laws
and Statutes as are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the preſervation of Wood and Timber; as
here they follow:</p>
                  <p>Statute 35 <hi>H.</hi> 8 17. There ſhall be left unfelled in
every acre of Copice or Under wood, which ſhall be felled at twenty four
yeers growths or under, twelve Standils of Oak: or if there be not ſo many
Oaks the number ſhall be made up of Elm, Aſh, Aſp, or Beech; which
Standils ſhall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be
felled, until they bear ten inches ſquar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> within thre foot of the ground, on pain that the
owner of the Wood ſhall forfeit for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Standil nor ſo left, 3
<hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d,</hi> and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Standil left, and afterwards cut down
before he come to that bigneſs as aforeſaid 3 <hi>s.</hi> 4 <hi>d.</hi> the
forfeitures to be divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <pb n="130" facs="tcp:115019:71"/>the King and the
Proſecutor.</p>
                  <p>None ſhall convertinto tillage or paſture any Underwood or
Cop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce, containing two acres
or above, and being two furlongs diſtant from the houſe of the Owner
thereof, or from the houſe whereunto ſuch wood doth belong on pain to
forfeit 40 <hi>s.</hi> for every acre ſo converted: <hi>it were well if this
were carefully looked after.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the owner of any ſuch Copice or Under wood may fell
Standils for his own uſe for building or repairing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Act.</p>
                  <p>The Lord of the Soyl ſhal not fell or cut down any Wood or
Copice, wherein o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have Common (except it be to his own uſe) before he
and the Commoners ſhall agree in the ſetting out a fourth part thereof, to
be imployed to the uſe of the Lord; and in caſe they cannot agree
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, two Juſtices of Peace appointed by the Seſſions ſhall have
power to call before them twelve of the Commoners and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and with
the conſent of the Lord and them, ſhall ſet our a fourth part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to
be incloſed by the Lord within one month after; and then to be felled at his
pleaſure, being ſubject to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſame Laws <pb n="131" facs="tcp:115019:71"/>and penalties upon breach
thereof, as other Copices before mentioned are: and if any Beaſt be
ſuffered to come into ſuch fourth part within ſeven yeers after it is
felled the Owner of ſuch Cattel ſhal forfeit for every ſuch Beaſt 4
<hi>d.</hi> &amp; if the Owner of any ſuch Copice or Wood, cut down any Trees
or Underwoods there, contrary to the form aforeſaid, he ſhall forfeit for
every tree ſo cut down 6 <hi>s.</hi> 8 <hi>d.</hi> All theſe forfeitures
are to be equally divided between the King and any one that will ſue for the
ſame in any Court of Record, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholſters.</head>
                  <p>None ſhall make to ſell, or offer to be ſold, any
Feather-Bed, Bolſter, or Pillow, except the ſame be ſtuffed with
dry-pulled Feathers, or clean Down only, without mingling of ſcalded
Feathers, fenne-Down, Thiſtle-Down, Sand, Lyme, Gravel, or other unlawful
corrupt ſtuff: on pain to forfeit the ſame ſo offered to be ſold, or
the value thereof.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe, none ſhall make to ſell or offer to be ſold
any Quilt, Mattreſs, or Cuſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſtuffed with any mingled ſtuff, other
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:115019:72"/>then Feathers, Wool, or Flocks alone; on pain to forfeit
the ſame ſo put to ſale, or the value. All which forfeitures are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to be divided between he King and any perſon that will ſue for the
ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Brokers, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers and Extortioners:</head>
                  <p>Three Birds of a Feather, not a pin to chuſe: theſe are
deſtructive <hi>Locuſts,</hi> that live by the ſweat of other mens brows:
the moſt wicked of all people; abhorrent, and againſt the Laws of God and
Nature: for <hi>uſurae legitimae ſunt illicitae:</hi> nay, <hi>nulla
uſura legitima eſt:</hi> thoſe uſuries which our Politick Laws allow,
though they may be ſaid to be lawful uſuries, and the moſt legitimate
<hi>quoad noſtram legem,</hi> yet they are illegitimate, and all unlawful
<hi>ſecundum legem Dei.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe moſt wretched people the Jews, having received from
God a moſt expreſs Command, not to oppreſs their brethren with Uſury,
they practiſe no vice more, and have ſpread their grangrene through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
almoſt all Nations, whither Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have ſcattered them; but
eſpecially, to the great ſhame of Chriſtians, have in 
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:115019:72"/>this reſpect found moſt imitation in
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And notwithſtanding the prudency and vigilant care of our
Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to cut off the <hi>Hydrean</hi> heads of theſe Serpents,
they carry their poyſon ſo ſubtilly as to deſtroy whole families under
the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended coverture of innocency in the eye of the Law: but yet certainly,
their skins may be pulled off, and their wickedneſs appear, if duly looked
after. I ſhall therefore firſt begin with the Brokers, who lend money upon
pledge or pawn, as they call it: that is, ſeldom exceeding the quarter, or a
little more, of the value of the thing ſo laid in pledge, ſhall be the
ſum of money ſo lent: and under this notion, the Brokers ſhops are the
harbors and receptacles of thieves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for they receive like hell, all that
comes, not caring whether the bringers be the right Owners or not, ſo there
appear a viſage of gain: and though the right Owner finde his own Goods in
their poſſeſſion, yet they under pretence of the alteration of
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, will not deliver them. But let them know, that the ſale of Goods
wrongfully gotten, to any Broker in <hi>London, Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
Southwark,</hi> or within two miles of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall not alter the
property the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:115019:73"/>
                  <p>And if any Broker, having received any ſuch Goods, ſhall
not upon the requeſt of the true Owner, truly diſcover them, how and when
he came by them, and to whom they are conveyed, he ſhall forfeit the double
value thereof to the Owner of the ſaid Goods, <hi>Stat.</hi> 1 <hi>Jac.</hi>
21.</p>
                  <p>But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s is
not all; for by an Act of the Jate Seſſions of Parliament holden at
<hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> in the County of <hi>Midd. Anno</hi> 1651<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it
is enacted and ordained, That no perſon or perſons, ſhall directly or
indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or by any craft or colour whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver take above 6 <hi>l.</hi>
for the loane or intereſt of 100 <hi>l.</hi> for a yeer, or over<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and
above that rate for a greater or a leſſer ſum, ſhall forfeit the treble
value of the money or goods ſo lent, to be divided between the Protector
&amp; any party that will ſue for the ſame in any Court of Record, by
Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Action of Deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,
Bill Plant or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. And if any Scrivener or Broker, ſhall take any
more then 5 <hi>s.</hi> for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of 100 <hi>l.</hi> for a year, or
according to that rate for a greater or leſſer ſum, ſhall forfeit 20
<hi>l.</hi> and the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llory.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheles ſo cunningly do theſe brokers and Uſurers
carry their deſigns, that <hi>viis &amp; <pb n="135" facs="tcp:115019:73"/>modis</hi> they
take at firſt peny after the rate of 30 <hi>l. per annum, per cent,</hi> and
as they handle the buſineſs, they make it amount to above 60 <hi>l. per
annum, per cent.</hi> beſides the trade of thoſe that let money at 2
<hi>s.</hi> in the pound, deducted for twenty weeks, and have their money
alſo paid weekly.</p>
                  <p>Well therefore were it to be wiſhed, and is much to be
deſired, that theſe offences were duely proſecuted, and this enormous
vice corrrected, ſo much conducing to the good of the Common-wealth, and
well-being of all people in general who muſt earn their bread before they eat
it.</p>
                  <p>Several other kinds of Extortion there are, eſpecially in
Bayliffs, under-Sheriffs, Goalers, Sergeants, and ſuch-like, which I ſhall
omit here, and leave them till another opportunity, becauſe their corruption
will fill up whole volumes: unleſs I be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their being reduced by
the diligent hand of Juſtice, as I hope ſhortly they will</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
